<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Omar&#39;s blog</title>
    <link>/posts/</link>
    <description>Omar&#39;s blog (Posts)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2023 14:35:04 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Thrall and Casta Paintings in the Context of Post-Colonial Theory</title>
      <link>/posts/casta/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2023 14:29:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/casta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To argue that a good work of art ought to faithfully, that is, realistically depict a concrete referent in the world is to lose sight of the fact this “realism” itself is inextricably linked to an interpretative process— the artist taking, or understanding the world to be a certain way. To speak of the artist’s representation of a given landscape, for example, is to speak concurrently of that artist&amp;rsquo;s production of it. This production is not, indeed cannot be, value-neutral since it both informs and is informed by socio-historical determinations. This is especially the case for a work of art—or more generally an artistic genre— whose object is indeterminate due to its constitutive otherness. And yet, this unrepresentability, far from inducing silence, is precisely that which draws artists towards the object in hordes. The representation of the unrepresentable, in this case, is not an exercise in artistic inventiveness or creativity, but rather has an explicitly political purpose. This is less a penchant to represent than categorize— it thus attempts to quell the artists—that is, a given cultures— anxieties about the objects essential slipperiness, its refusal to be reconciled with that which already exists. This object, then, can be used — for the purposes of the artist—to adumbrate the social mores of that culture. One can, for example, look at casta paintings in order to better understand the racial prejudices and hierarchies that were prevalent in New Spain at the time of their production.  The depiction of social fixity in casta paintings, however, belied a society that, as R. Douglas Cope argues  in The Limits of Racial Domination, “retained  much…cultural autonomy” to such an extent, in fact, that Indigenous peoples employed “highly localized ethnic referents as late as the eighteenth century” (Cope, 4-5). These paintings, then, were not simply symbolizing already-existing racial categories so much as attempting to establish an epistemological grid through which fixed social identities could be ascribed to persons begotten of inter-ethnic or inter-racial marriages so that this cultural autonomy could be resisted. Casta paintings  assuage and calm the colonist by providing the illusion that everything is under control— nothing escapes the watchful eye of the artist. In this essay, I will discuss three casta paintings in light of their contemporary reception (as well as the prejudices that gave birth to them) in Thrall, allowing the aforementioned themes to guide my analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trethewey deftly unsettles the narrative structure of various casta paintings through poetry that speaks an unwritten, that is, unrepresented history. She speaks in Taxonomy, for example,  through and of various persons depicted in casta paintings— “the morisca, the lobo, the chino,/ sambo, albino”  (Trethewey).  These are, to be sure, for the colonists, scientific categories; a veritable “[g]uidebook to the colony”, scrupulously kept, in which everyone has his place, as it were. There is no room for doubt or error in such a system. The poem continues and the reader is confronted with a line-break after the cataloging of various “mixed bloods”, perhaps expecting the list to continue into the next stanza, but, Trethewey instead writes “the no-te-entiendo—the/ I don’t understand you (Trethewey). One should not understand Trethewey here as simply refusing these categories. Her argument is far more radical. The “I don’t understand you” — this absolute unintelligibility— is immanent to the naming process itself. The emphasis should be placed on the “the” that precedes “I don’t understand you” since it is on the basis of this article that the reader knows that “I don’t understand you” is not an assertion but actually denotes a subject position.  “The I don’t understand you” in fact completes the list rather than straightforwardly rejects it. Is Trethewey, then, acquiescing to the colonists&amp;rsquo; categories? This is far from the case. It is precisely in completing the list that Trethewey reveals its constitutive, ineradicable incompleteness. As such, Trethewey herself does not aspire, in her poetry, to completeness. She recognizes that this seemingly hopeful counter-narrative is, at its base, a mangled appropriation of the colonist’s own methods. She thus rejects the simplifying hopefulness of counter-narrative by forwarding instead a critical register of hope. Her words, as Olga Dugan argues in Renegade Poetics, Southscapes, and the Poetry of History in Natasha Trethewey’s Thrall”,  “prick and wound without necessarily coming together as an orderly and healing whole” (Dugan, 314).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The colonist might dream of wholeness, a perfect system, but will always be at least one category shy of his dream, since this category is simultaneously the system&amp;rsquo;s condition of possibility and impossibility. It is its condition of possibility insofar that it allows the colonist to begin the naming process, to metabolize difference. But it is also its condition of impossibility since it never allows the colonist to finish this process. If this system has a telos, it is one that is essentially comic: the final category reached— “the I don’t understand you” — reveals the ridiculousness of assuming that one might ever reach a final category. She thus restores a sort of revolutionary dignity to the colonized: they are, in such a system, an Other awaiting metabolization, but they also herald the news that this metabolization is to be eternally deferred. Colonial society can know no (epistemological) peace in the face of its Other, which it itself posits.  It is in this sense that Trethewey rejects the “catalog of mixed bloods” and critically approaches casta paintings (Trethewey). She rehabilitates not the paintings themselves but the subjects depicted therein. Indeed, one could argue, as Joseph Millichap does in ““Love and Knowledge”: Daughters and Fathers in Natasha Trethewey’s Thrall” that “Thrall becomes Trethewey’s own book of castas” (Millichap, 195).  But this rehabilitation, as mentioned above, is carried out in an entirely negative and critical way: she does not offer  “putatively “positive” images as a counter to racist taxonomy. Instead, she exposes the process of “seeing blackness” as the central problem” (Jones, 408).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take, for example, the painting “From Cambujo and Mulatta, an Albarazo is Born” and the manner in which Blackness is depicted in it— the family is shown to be devoid of all dignity, in a state of desperate penury. Casta paintings often depict a domestic setting— and, provided that a Spanish individual is present in the painting, this setting is quite lavish. The family in this painting however— composed of a Cambujo, Mulatta, and an Albarazo— are permanently homeless. The absence of the Spanish, that is, of whiteness, is the absence of a domestic space. The colonized can only occupy the margins of society, eternally wandering. To wander these physical margins is to also occupy the outskirts of culture itself: the colonized have no time for creative pursuits, they are too busy surviving. Notice, for example, the (presumably Spanish) couple playing guitar in the background of the painting. This, of course, is to be contrasted with the couple in the foreground who are in tattered, worn clothes. Even their child, with outstretched arms, hesitates to join them— such is, according to this painting, the fate of a union between two people of  darker complexion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is this fate radically altered if one of the members of the family were Spanish? This is a question answered by the painting “From Spanish and Black, Mulatta is Born”. Depicted in this painting is violent marital conflict. The Spanish man&amp;rsquo;s Black wife is grabbing him by the locks of his hairs and wields a kitchen utensil in her other hand in order to strike him. The man is visibly shocked and attempts to distance himself from his wife. Their daughter is in distress and begs for her mother to calm down. This painting, very clearly, serves as a warning. It admonishes the Spanish man who could be so foolish as to marry a Black woman, essentially proclaiming, “if you are to go down this path, expect nothing less!”. The in-born savage nature of the mother— who knows nothing but strife— is demonstrated to be hostile to a domestic, idyllic life. Both of these paintings are thus very similar since they condemn most harshly those marriages that are deemed undesirable. In the first painting, the possibility of such a couple ever entering civil society is immediately foreclosed. In the second, the consequences of forcing such an entry is demonstrated in the form of a discordant marriage— one cannot expect, so the painting tells us, a harmonious union between a savage and an individual endowed with a pure soul. The colonized subjects, in both paintings, are captives of the colonial imagination, their inferiority presented as though it were a natural fact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How, then, does Trethewey begin the rehabilitative process? In On Captivity, Trethewey reveals that far from being natural, this order is one that is completely contingent and violently enforced. She does this by describing a historical event in which the roles are reversed, so to speak. The “savage” is now the master, whereas the former masters are captives whose bodies are “rendered/plain as the natives” (Trethewey). Is it possible to speak of the natural inferiority, the cowardice, of the settlers in this scenario? Or have they simply found themselves— through no fault of their own— in unfavorable circumstances? Trethewey does not spend any time spewing vitriol or exacting poetic revenge. Nor does she sympathize with the captive settlers. She only observes the irony of their situation. If, in “From Cambujo and Mulatta, an Albarazo is Born”, the family is shown to wear the simplest of clothes, it is in On Captivity that the settlers find themselves in a far more scandalous position— utter nakedness. Was it not in a similar state of nakedness that the settlers first encountered the Natives? Was this lack of propriety not taken as the greatest offense to European sensibilities? Did it not require that the European bring the Native to knowledge of the truth of the Bible? One can read On Captivity—essentially a meditation about the fortuitous swapping of roles— as a speculative response to these questions. Now it is the all-mighty Europeans— not the Native— who, “Naked as newborns” are “brought to knowledge” (Trethewey). And what is the settlers only recourse in such a situation? He has no choice but to cover himself with “the torn leaves of Genesis” (Trethewey). Those hallowed pages that spurred the European on in his effort to civilize the wretched now hang from his naked body. He finds himself in a state that he sought to purge from the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is, however, one might argue, to the painting “From Spanish and Mestiza, Castiza is Born” an almost redemptive quality. It is not a representation of poverty nor marital conflict. Rather, one observes an elegantly clothed couple. The Spanish husband points beyond, carrying a rifle on his shoulder. Here we have a portrait of the vigorous, restless conquistador who ventures into the unknown. The wife bows her head obligingly, holding her daughter to her breast. This painting, one might continue, finally represents Indigeneity in a good light. Trethewey criticizes this position in the poem Taxonomy. That the Spanish admit someone of Indigenous ancestry into their ranks does not speak to their emancipatory ambitions. The Mestiza is only tolerated because she has Spanish blood, and can be used for the purposes of re-introducing purity back into a bloodline: “from a Spaniard and an Indian/a mestizo;/ from a mestizo and a Spaniard,/ a castizo;/ from a castizo and a Spaniard,/ a Spaniard” (Trethewey). The mestiza and her daughter, the castiza, are instrumentalized for this purpose. If she is tolerated it is only because she bears this potential, and must be coaxed into actualizing it— she is purity twice removed. She is tolerated insofar as she promises her own negation. She gives birth not to someone like herself, but someone who heralds this negation, who is one step closer to attaining the wholeness of purity. She gives birth, then, so that there is no longer anyone like her. She is caught in a system that is “unethical… due to a propensity to exert power over the Other, defining and thus reducing the Other to what she is not, annihilating difference” (Valenzuela-Mendoza, 338). It is this absence of a proper ethical relation (in the Levinasian sense), as Valenzuela-Mendoza argues, that results in the instrumentalization of the mestiza mother, her being treated as an object. The castiza, too, is in the most precarious of situations.  There is, for her, no “[anxious balance] between love and knowledge”, since the self-annihilating knowledge she bears does not “[incline] towards love” — she can never know maternal love because she is required to “turn toward the father… to the promise of blood… to purity” which is only “one generation away” (Millichamp, 196; Trethewey).  In doing so, she slips from “her mother’s careful grip” (Trethewey).  This painting, far from representing Indigeneity in a good light, reproduces “the mind of the colony” (Trethewey).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Casta paintings, then, were in a sense, a guide on how to navigate unprecedented difference in a community— a propaedeutic for discerning “purity” amidst innumerable so-called impure persons. To read them differently, to look for signs in them of an emancipatory logic, is something that Trethewey, in Thrall, sternly warns against. One must instead turn to Indigenous art if one searches for a site of resistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;works-cited&#34;&gt;Works Cited&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cope, R. Douglas. The Limits of Racial Domination: Plebeian Society in Colonial Mexico City, 1660-1720. University of Wisconsin Press, 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eloisa Valenzuela-Mendoza (2019) ‘The wages of empire’: American inventions of mixed-race identities and Natasha Trethewey’s Thrall (2012), African and Black Diaspora: An International Journal, 12:3, 337-354, DOI: 10.1080/17528631.2019.1611321&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trethewey, Natasha D. Thrall: Poems. Mariner Books/Houghton Mifflin Harcourt, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JONES, META DUEWA. “REFRAMING EXPOSURE: NATASHA TRETHEWEY’S FORMS OF ENCLOSURE.” ELH, vol. 82, no. 2, 2015, pp. 407–29. JSTOR, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jstor.org/stable/24477792&#34;&gt;http://www.jstor.org/stable/24477792&lt;/a&gt;. Accessed 26 Mar. 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Millichap, J. (2013). &amp;ldquo;Love and knowledge&amp;rdquo;: Daughters and fathers in natasha trethewey&amp;rsquo;s thrall. Southern Quarterly, 50(4), 189-207,224. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;http://myaccess.library.utoronto.ca/login?qurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.proquest.com%2Fscholarly-journals%2Flove-knowledge-daughters-fathers-natasha%2Fdocview%2F1464666755%2Fse-2%3Faccountid%3D14771&#34;&gt;http://myaccess.library.utoronto.ca/login?qurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.proquest.com%2Fscholarly-journals%2Flove-knowledge-daughters-fathers-natasha%2Fdocview%2F1464666755%2Fse-2%3Faccountid%3D14771&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Olga Dugan. “RENEGADE POETICS, SOUTHSCAPES, AND THE POETRY OF HISTORY IN NATASHA TRETHEWEY’S THRALL.” The Journal of African American History, vol. 98, no. 2, 2013, pp. 304–19. JSTOR, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5323/jafriamerhist.98.2.0304&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5323/jafriamerhist.98.2.0304&lt;/a&gt;. Accessed 26 Mar. 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Utopia and History in Benjamin and Adorno</title>
      <link>/posts/adorno/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2023 13:58:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/adorno/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the works of both Benjamin and Adorno, there is a radical departure from a salvific conception of history insofar as this salvation presupposes the unity of history and a concept of progress by which historical events are interpreted as being directed towards a certain terminal point. This theory of history, from which Adorno and Benjamin distance themselves, is one that is, at least formally, theological. However, the attempt to move beyond such a theory of history does not begin with these two thinkers. As Karl Löwith argues in Meaning and History, modern philosophy of history, beginning in the 18th century, attempts to ground  philosophy of history not in “revelation and faith” but the “empirical method of Voltaire” (Löwith 1949, 1). And yet, for Löwith, there is no true conceptual evolution in this development. Modern philosophy’s interpretation of history is still indebted to the theological paradigm insofar as it merely secularizes the latter’s “eschatological pattern” instead of going beyond it (Löwith 1949, 2). Faith in the Kingdom of God is replaced with faith in ineluctable progress; modern philosophy of history seems to be a farcical repetition of its disciplinary antecedent. What, then, prevents Adorno and Benjamin’s theory of history from relapsing into a theology that nevertheless proclaims itself free from such pretensions? That is, how do they move beyond a salvific conception of history that does not simply mimic the false triumph of modern philosophy of history?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For both Adorno and Benjamin, philosophy of history is not a discipline internally riven by, on the one hand, a predilection to theology and on the other, a scientific method. It is at the moment that one assumes that one can simply abandon these supposedly facile precepts that one is most beholden to them. This is, of course, observed in the inability of modern philosophy of history to move beyond that which it desires to supersede. Both thinkers are able to avoid this impasse by dialectising this internal division. Take, for example, the first theses in Benjamin’s Theses on the Philosophy of History (hereafter, Theses) which can be read as a critique of a dogmatic historical materialism that guarantees the victory of socialism by dint of immutable and mechanistic laws of history. It is clear that the positivism of this method resembles the modern philosophies of history criticized by Löwith, and is thus equally affected by all their attendant shortcomings. This is a historical materialism that, despite its ostensible positivism, begets its own theology. However, one will notice that in the Theses, Benjamin does not reject theology in toto. To do so would be to fall into the very same conceptual trap he is trying to avoid. As Margaret Cohen argues in Profane Illumination: Walter Benjamin and the Paris of Surrealist Revolution, Benjamin recognizes that theology (and various theological concepts such as salvation or redemption)— the “realm of a culture’s ghosts and phantasms” — is not a “mirage to be dispelled” but rather “a significant and rich field of social production” (Cohen 1993, 11).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benjamin does not subtract the theological from historical materialism, but, by putting these two seemingly disparate theoretical frameworks into a relationship with each other, transforms both. Likewise, Adorno’s refusal to give discursive formulation to a utopian future, approaching it only negatively, can be attributed to his “adherence to the Jewish Bilderverbot” (Benzaquén, 150). Just as followers of the Jewish faith refuse to speak God’s name outside a liturgical context since the messianic age is yet to come, Adorno remains silent in the face of the task of outlining a utopian future since, for him,  “true reconciliation could never be achieved by philosophy alone” (Jay 1973, 262). For Adorno too, the invocation of theological precepts is never done for its own sake but rather to interrogate and explore the relationship between theology and historical materialism. To wit: reconciliation is, for both thinkers, an eminently Marxist category since it was Marx himself who first refused to give a positive description of a utopian, that is, reconciled, future (Benzaquén, 151).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, one might object to the groundlessness of Benjamin and Adorno’s  critical theory of history (arising precisely out of the aforementioned refusal). It appears that both undermine their theoretical projects by not grounding it in something stable or constant such as a unified horizon, a normative foundation, or set of transcendental conditions. The response comes, from both thinkers, that these conditions are not locatable in history. How can a theory of history utilize a language that lacks history, leading history to become mythologized, which, as Adorno points out, is connected to the philosophy of the fascists? In this respect, both are explicitly against the idea of grounding their respective critical theories of history, that is, both refuse the self-reflexive defense of the presuppositions or bases of their theories. At the core of this view is a rejection of the Kuhnian model of scientific progress and crisis whereby there is an opposition in the practice of science (whether natural or social) between the “normal” scientific programme of problem-solving and the discovery of an anomaly that triggers a disciplinary crisis, resulting in a so-called paradigm shift. Instead, critical theory, for Adorno and Benjamin (and indeed, much of the early critical theorists of the Frankfurt School) is always already in crisis— there is no normal scientific period. This informs Adorno and Benjamin’s respective methods insofar as the concept of history in their works is never taken for granted, so to speak, but is always interrogated and problematized. They do not begin their inquiries into history by beginning with a self-identical, or common-sense notion of history. One cannot, for both thinkers, distill an “essence” of a concept from its historical appearance— this applies even to the very concept of history itself. Such a philosophy of history—one that claims to have achieved a universal or holistic perspective of social totality— merely lapses into a contemplative position; investigating essences detached from their historical and social contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For philosophy to become social it must cease being purely contemplative. Only Marxism can do this, that is, only Marixsm, for Benjamin and Adorno, unites theory and praxis by providing a shared problematic.  The shared problematic is capitalist domination. Critical theory proper, then, as social philosophy, must have a critique of capitalism. That is, critical theory must show how modern conceptions of historical progress, far from being self-evident, neutral facts, are symptomatic of a particular historical juncture. This is why it is not possible, in critical theory, to see as separate enterprises  the critique of a certain conception of history and the critique of capitalism. One needs to keep one&amp;rsquo;s critical eye, as it were, on the system that produces the concepts that one is trying to overcome. It is not enough, however, to have a shared problematic for doing critical theory. A shared goal is also necessary. This shared goal is communism, i.e., utopia— this is the precondition for all critical activity; it is neither identified with the present world, nor removed from it so far that it can never be reached.  It is, then, to Marx himself that the messianism of Benjamin and the utopian thrust of Adorno’s thought is owed. Marx famously wrote that “[c]ommunism is for us not a state of affairs which is to be established, an ideal to which reality [will] have to adjust itself. We call communism the real movement which abolishes the present state of things” (Marx, German Ideology).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, there is, at the heart of Benjamin’s Theses, a “deeply Marxian question” (Khatib, 47). As Sami Khatib argues in “The Time of Capital and the Messiancity of Time: Marx with Benjamin”, Benjamin asks “how [is one to] conceive of the relationship of the political presence of class struggle and authentic historical experience without relying on a meta- or trans-historical standpoint” (Khatib, 47). Several things become clear if we take seriously Khatib&amp;rsquo;s understanding of Benjamin’s aims in the Theses. First, the shared problematic provided by critical theory, that is capitalist domination, is centered in a matter that appears to be wholly theoretical, and thus far removed from the realm of politics. What Khatib, in his assessment of Benjamin’s project underlines, is that the theoretical is always already political. Capitalism (falsely) presupposes the universality of its own “mode of historicization”; however, the time of capital, or capital-time, far from being such a universal determination is shot through with the particularity of its condition (Khatib, 48).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capital-time is universal only in the sense that it organizes relations under capitalism and reproduces its ideological representations. And since this universality is not natural, it is contestable: “[h]istory is the subject of a structure whose site is not homogeneous, empty time, but time filled by the presence of the now” (Benjamin 2019, 205). What Benjamin derides, then, as the “homogenous, empty time” of the Social Democrats is his specific theoretical elaboration of capital-time, and the “now-time” is what he opposes to it. If Benjamin critiques this empty time, it is primarily due to its concept of historical progress. Since time is understood to be continuous and linear, the present is constantly displacing, or rather, erasing the past— history evolves indefinitely. It is clear how this concept of time is closely allied with the teleology of salvific conceptions of history. This is a conception of time, however, that can never deliver on its promise of redemption since for mankind to be redeemed, it would need to receive “the fullness of its past… [the] past must become citable in all its moments” (Benjamin 2019, 197). The historical materialist, then, is not a historian if the latter’s task is (despite their scientific pretensions) to narrate history— that is, imbue it with symbolic meaning by ordering historical events.  The historian deems some events significant and thus worthy of further investigation, so that they can claim their rightful places in history. If the historian is to be trusted, history is only the sequence of such significant events— events that are deemed significant only in their relation to the end of history which they all help realize; a nebulous, as yet undefined terminus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The historical materialist, on the other hand, does not narrate— he chronicles. He does not distinguish between the significant and the insignificant (indeed this distinction itself is rendered meaningless in his work). The flattening of the historians narrative is not an act of political neutrality, but is instead a revolutionary act par excellence. As Benjamin writes, “[n]ot man or men but the struggling, oppressed class is the depository of historical knowledge” (Benjamin 2019, 204). The historical materialist refuses to side with those whom history has deemed the victors. Adorno similarly argues that the task of the natural historian (who is identical to the historical materialist in all but name) is to construct constellations that contest the hegemonic narratives of the historian. In his “The Idea of Natural History” argues that an aporetic conclusion is reached if we understand the concepts of nature and history as ontological essences that are completely separate from each other. Max Pensky, in “Natural History: The Life and Afterlife of a Concept in Adorno”  argues that, according to Adorno, once we posit nature as the ground of history—that which is “beyond thought” — and history as a “wholly human process of self-constitution” we essentially give up on a proper philosophical, that is, dialectical, understanding of both (Pensky, 230). While Benjamin does not treat the concept of history in relation to nature in the Theses, both texts make similar arguments. Adorno argues that to ontologize history (as the historian whom Benjamin rebukes does) is to flee from it. He demonstrates that the question that supposedly confronts the philosopher (is ontology to be given priority over history, or history over ontology?) is in fact a false one. This tension is relieved through the construction of a “dialectical crossing-point” through which each concept can pass into its other  (Pensky, 232).  The narrative prepared by the historian, for example, does not go through this dialectical crossing-point since, by virtue of its claim to totality and ultimate meaning, it resides strictly within the realm of ontology— without passing into history.
The solutions offered by Benjamin and Adorno to move beyond this impasse are also very similar in nature— the goal is to fracture the wholeness of these narratives. It is important to recall at this point that insofar as both thinkers are committed to thinking utopia that the solutions offered will remain entirely negative: one narrative is not swapped for another, since to do so would be to make use of the categories of the present. The historical constellations that Adorno writes of, for example, can be said to be both historical and natural (that is, ontological) in the sense that they generate only “concrete, singular, and utterly empirical facts and bodies… incapable of being incorporated into a meaning-giving conception of historical continuity and experience” (Pensky, 234). That which is usually passed over as insignificant, transient, or contingent is now accorded the highest dignity since it inaugurates discontinuity and thus cannot be incorporated into the symbolic world of the historian. It is in this sense that Adorno’s constellation can be likened to Benjamin’s own solution, the dialectical image. In Arcades Project, Benjamin writes that “[h]istory decays into images, not into stories” (Benjamin, 476). The standstill— which Benjamin identifies with utopia— induced by the dialectical image, arises precisely from the refusal to narrativise, or, as Benjamin puts it, by giving priority to image over metaphor (the latter being the building blocks of narrative).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These metaphors, ordered in a certain way, tell “the sequence of events like the beads of a rosary” (Benjamin 2019, 208). The empty time which is Benjamin’s object of critique is not literally empty but rather filled to the brim with metaphors— what one might call “tradition” — that constitute the “narrative of boundless progress” (Chowdhury, 98). But if the historical materialist is to treat tradition with the utmost caution, how is he to cite the past that is contained within it? To answer this question, it is necessary to turn to Benjamin’s treatment of the concept of repetition, which, in the Theses he defines as a “tiger’s leap into the past”, that is, a repetition that is no longer beholden to homogenous, empty time (Benjamin 2019, 205). For the historian, to repeat is to retrieve (always retroactively) those events which have occurred in the linear continuum which he himself has constructed. The historian likes to think of himself as possessing a pure gaze through which he extracts historical essences. However, for Benjamin (and in this regard he is entirely indebted to Marx), repetition always introduces something new into the world that disrupts the linearity of homogenous, empty time. Repetition deals not in essences but masks and costumes:  as Benjamin writes in the Theses, “[t]hus to Robespierre ancient Rome was a past charged with the time of the now which he blasted out of the continuum of history. The French revolution viewed itself as Rome incarnate. It evoked ancient Rome the way fashion evokes costumes of the past” (Benjamin 2019, 205).  Similarly, Adorno argues in “The Idea of Natural History”, that if a dialectical crossing point is not constructed between the concepts of nature and history, one will understand the former as “mythical…archaic” and the latter as “that which surfaces as dialectically and emphatically new” (Adorno, 100). That is, when the dialectical relationship between the two is severed, so is the relationship between repetition and the new— history is understood to be a wholly autonomous process of self-constitution. Adorno argues that the contemporary relevance of myth undoes the fantasy of history as the production of the new ex nihilo (this also applies to the historians treatment of tradition as simply a curious artefact). Since the natural historian and historical materialist do not simply reach into the past to retrieve essences, the repetition of myth in order to introduce something new into history does occur through the repetition of that which already is (the myth is not simply transposed into the present), rather, the myth itself is only constituted or actualized “in the process of the construction of the present” (Pensky, 237). In the example given by Benjamin, however, the repetition “takes place in an arena where the ruling class give the commands” (Benjamin 2019, 205). If, as mentioned above, we understand Benjamin’s dialectical image and Adorno’s constellation as not only theoretical, but political determinations, then it is the duty of the revolutionary and not the ruling class to situate itself in the non-synchronous time of the now— this is the site of the struggle between the victor and the oppressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;works-cited&#34;&gt;Works Cited&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chowdhury, A. (2014). &amp;ldquo;Memory, Modernity, Repetition: Walter Benjamin’s Ethico-Political History&amp;rdquo;. In Post-deconstructive Subjectivity and History. Leiden, The Netherlands: Brill. doi: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1163/9789004260047_005&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1163/9789004260047_005&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Max Pensky (2004) Natural History: the Life and Afterlife of a Concept in Adorno, Critical Horizons, 5:1, 227-258, DOI: 10.1163/1568516042653620&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Khatib, Sami. “The Time of Capital and the Messianicity of Time: Marx with Benjamin.” Studies in Social and Political Thought, pp. 46–69.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BENZAQUÉN, ADRIANA S. “Thought and Utopia in the Writings of Adorno, Horkheimer, and Benjamin.” Utopian Studies, vol. 9, no. 2, 1998, pp. 149–61. JSTOR, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jstor.org/stable/20719766&#34;&gt;http://www.jstor.org/stable/20719766&lt;/a&gt;. Accessed 7 May 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benjamin, Walter, et al. The Arcades Project. Belknap Press, 1999.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benjamin, Walter, et al. Illuminations. The Bodley Head Ltd, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Loewith, Karl. Meaning in History. Univ. of Chicago Pr., 1949.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cohen, Margaret. Profane Illumination: Walter Benjamin and the Paris of Surrealist Revolution. University of California Press, 1995.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marx, Karl, et al. The German Ideology. Progress Publishers, 1976.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on the Concept of Totality in Heidegger</title>
      <link>/posts/heidegger/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2023 14:15:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/heidegger/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The concepts of  “end” and “totality”  (as well as the relationship that figures between the two) are central to Heidegger’s analysis of death. And yet he wants to disabuse us (as he is wont to do) of thinking about these concepts in a manner that would be altogether unsuitable for his analysis. Indeed, to understand Dasein’s “end” qua perishing, or disappearance, is to lose sight of death, since death, for Heidegger, much like the analytic of Dasein, is to be understood ontologically; that is, as an ontological possibility. Now, it is true that Heidegger acknowledges that his ontological characterization of death “signifies nothing, so long as a corresponding ontical potentiality-for-Being has not been demonstrated in Dasein itself” (Heidegger 1962, 311). As such, I will, in this paper, investigate both the existential and existentiell dimensions of death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heidegger begins his analysis of death with a detailed investigation of its character as that which is “outstanding”. To be sure, this is not a quality unique to death, since all the  possibilities of Dasein must be similarly outstanding. The crucial difference between death and other possibilities is that death is the only non-actualizable possibility of Dasein— it is that which “is the possibility of the impossibility of any existence at all (Heidegger 1962, 307). But if death is a phenomenon that is ontologically constitutive of Dasein, we cannot treat it as though it were yet another “event” in the course of Dasein’s life, nor is understanding death qua the biological cessation of life appropriate for Heidegger’s purposes. Death, rather, is Dasein’s end. However, Dasein does not simply “arrive” at this end, since in arriving at its end Dasein no longer is. This is also why Dasein’s “incompleteness”, its “not-yet” is constitutive of its Being: Dasein cannot be whole, or “together” when death finally displaces this “not-yet” because it is when “this “not-yet” has been filled… that Dasein is no longer” (Heidegger 1962, 287). Dasein, then is never simply at its end but always towards its end: “its “not-yet” belongs to it” (Heidegger 1962, 287).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heidegger then writes that, “[i]n death, Dasein has not been fulfilled nor has it simply disappeared” (Heidegger 1962, 289). This is a perplexing claim. We know that death is the negation of Dasein since death is the impossibility of Dasein— but there is now a proviso attached to this: negation does not lead to Dasein disappearance. Recall that death is not just the impossibility of Dasein but rather the possibility of this impossibility. As Mark Tanzer argues in “Heidegger on death as a deficient mode”, Dasein is able to retain its ontological identity even in death since “that end is Dasein itself” (Tanzer, 27). The fact that Dasein does not disappear, nor change ontologically in death is what separates it from mere ready-to-hand or present-at-hand objects. For example, if an object loses one of its essential qualities and thereby meets its end, it loses its previous ontological identity (it disappears)  and assumes another one (Tanzer, 27). This is, of course, not the case for Dasein— Dasein, paradoxically, does not disappear in the face of its identity-loss. “Death”, writes Heidegger, “is a way to be, which Dasein takes over as soon as it is” (Heidegger 1962, 289). To say that the end belongs to Dasein, that it is a Being-towards-death, means that this impossibility— death— is structurally, that is, ontologically, inscribed in the very concept of Dasein.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That death reveals itself as Dasein’s “ownmost… non-relational” possibility “which is not to be outstripped” as soon as Dasein is, can be attributed to Dasein’s thrownness (Heidegger 1962, 294). It is entirely possible that Dasein relates to its thrownness into death in a manner which is evasive, so that it can be said of Dasein that it flees from death (Heidegger 1962, 299). This fleeing, of course, does not take the form of a physical action. Dasein, in relating to its death inauthentically, occludes from its view death’s radical singularity, its unrepresentability, and the fact that death always already belongs to it. Rather, it treats death as “just a “case of death””, as though it were reconcilable with the rest of Dasein’s experience. Or perhaps Dasein broods over death, taking it seriously, announcing to himself and others that he is preparing for his death by giving alms and living righteously. This latter way of comporting oneself towards death in a pious manner is no less inauthentic than the former’s “untroubled indifference” (Heidegger 1962, 299). Merely being certain of one&amp;rsquo;s death does not suffice in relating to death authentically. For in both of these cases, Dasein does not deny the possibility of its death, indeed, it is certain of it (“[n]obody doubts that one dies”), and yet, Dasein flees from it (Heidegger 1962, 299). This cannot be said to be an authentic certainty. To be certain of death in an empirical, or apodictic manner is still to fail to relate to it authentically since death is not an object of theoretical knowledge (Heidegger 1962, 302). Indeed, such certainty is symptomatic of Dasein’s fallenness and, as such, falls short of that “primordial signification”, that is, Being-certain (Heidegger 1962, 300).  Heidegger does not treat death as an event that occurs since Dasein is not around to experience its death. Rather,  the only possible solution is an understanding of Dasein’s being-towards its end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To assume this authentic relationship with death, Dasein must be in anticipation. This results in anxiety, which is a result of Dasein’s recognition of the non-relationality of death— a recognition that individualizes Dasein (Heidegger 1962, 308). Moreover, it is precisely anxiety that explodes the horizon of average everydayness, thereby opening up the choice for Dasein to be authentic or inauthentic. If to speak of death “existentially” is to speak of being-towards-death as a universal determination of Dasein, to speak of it “existentielly” is to speak of the specific mode that determines the nature or the character of Dasein’s relationship to death. That is, the existential is basic, while the existentiell is modificatory. Authentic being-towards-death reveals to Dasein its freedom, which is the locus of non-relationality. In this mode, the entirety of the world is understood according to Dasein’s ownmost possibility. One might, at this point, interpret authenticity as a complete negation of the they-self since to be authentic seems to imply complete autonomy and a severance from the influence of others.  However, authenticity is only a modification of the way Dasein is with others and is thus not a negation of the they-self. Recall that the they-self is an existential structure and so its negation is impossible: Dasein is the they-self. Authenticity is only a modification of this relation, one however, that Dasein can never maintain for too long. Can one, for example, remain in an authentic mode indefinitely if it is anxiety that allows for one to enter into it? Will Dasein not eventually fall back, so to speak, onto the they-self?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Death, one can say, then, is the principal operator of self-disclosure. The question of “how to be” is only a question that can be asked by Dasein. And, unless it is possible for a being to not be, one cannot ask what it means to be. Death, consequently, is not a defect but is rather the possibility of being authentic. Does Dasein ever take up this challenge? In other words, how does Dasein become authentic? If one searches for, in Being and Time, a propaedeutic to comporting oneself authentically, as though it were a text filled with edifying and instructional ethical propositions, then one has not even begun to understand Heidegger’s intention in writing it. For authenticity is a site of radical indeterminacy, any concrete specification of Dasein’s ownmost possibility would be to slip back into the they-self. In explicating authenticity, Heidegger is only attempting to locate this as a possibility that dasein can demand. The content of this demand, however, is never specifiable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This demand is produced, according to Heidegger, by the call to conscience. Just as the demand itself, the call has no determinate content. The conscience, as is usually understood, is a faculty of the soul with definitive operations; its activity is prescriptive, resulting in concrete actions. This is not how Heidegger thinks of conscience. Conscience is important to Heidegger’s project insofar as it can motivate Dasein’s authenticity. This is why Heidegger refers to the conscience as “an attestation of Dasein’s ownmost potentiality-for-Being” (Heidegger 1962, 324). And while conscience, given its relation to authenticity, appears at first to be an individual phenomenon, Heidegger surprisingly writes that “[w]hen Dasein is resolute, it can be the ‘conscience’ of Others” (Heidegger 1962, 344). A Dasein that, through resoluteness, has “chosen” its freedom by overcoming the they-self can assume a position of authority, leading others to heed the call of their conscience. It seems that, according to Heidegger, such an individual bears an enormous responsibility: the establishment of an “authentic” community. As Heidegger writes, “[o]nly by authentically Being-their-selves in resoluteness can people authentically be with one another— not by ambiguous and jealous stipulations and talkative fraternizing in the “they” and in what “they” want to undertake (Heidegger 1962, 345). But this formulation leaves the reader with various questions, which I will end with.  It would appear that the authentic community serves more as a regulative ideal— if authenticity is linked to anxiety such that an individual is never always authentic, could the same not be said of a community? Or is an authentic community established through an elimination of the they-self? In what manner is the authentic individual— supposedly the one who establishes the authentic community— to go about fulfilling his political function?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Theodicy in Kant’s Religion within the Boundaries of Mere Reason</title>
      <link>/posts/kant/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2023 14:10:16 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/kant/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the Groundwork of the Metaphysics of Morals (hereafter, Groundwork), Kant differentiates between maxims that are determined by one’s inclinations and those that are grounded in practical reason. He writes that, “[t]hus common human reason is impelled to leave its sphere… on practical grounds… in order to receive there intelligence and distinct instruction regarding the source of this principle and its correct determination in contrast with maxims based on need and inclination” (Groundwork, 39). It is clear, then, from this passage, that inclinations can never be the ground of the principle of duty—any action that is carried in accordance with one&amp;rsquo;s inclinations is morally worthless. It could be that giving into a certain inclination is in an individual&amp;rsquo;s best interest. However, even if the action that one carries out as a result of one&amp;rsquo;s acquiescence were praiseworthy, it cannot be said to have any moral worth. Kant gives the example of the inclination of self-preservation. Every human being is, unquestionably, inclined to preserve his life. But, Kant argues, even this universal inclination is still devoid of “moral worth” and is “on the same footing as other inclinations”  if the action taken to preserve one&amp;rsquo;s life is not from duty (Groundwork, 25). Conversely, take the example of a person who experiences the gravest suffering such that it “extinguishes all compassion for the fate of others”, and yet,  in spite of this suffering he is able to “benefit others in need” (Groundwork, 25). In such a case, it can be said of this person that they have acted from duty, that is, from an a priori practical principle, and not simply in accordance with their inclination (even if this inclination seemingly conforms with duty). From the Groundwork, one gets the sense that, for Kant, inclinations are anathema; an abhorrent aspect of our empirical selves and thus worthy of the most serious condemnation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, Kant goes so far as to argue that an inclination is that which opposes, or, at the very least, cannot be considered within the set of things that grant humanity its “absolute worth” (Groundwork, 85). Kant argues that every human being possesses an “absolute worth” and must accordingly be treated “as an end in itself” (Groundwork, 85). Both inclinations themselves and their objects are excluded from this ethical determination. Consequently, Kant writes that “to be…free from them must… be the universal wish of every rational being (Groundwork, 85). It is in a later text— Religion within the Boundaries of Mere Reason (hereafter, Religion) — that Kant’s perspective on inclinations and their role in leading an ethical life undergoes a radical change. He writes, concerning the ground of the evil of philosophical chiliasm, that it “cannot be placed, as is commonly done, in the sensuous nature of the human being, and in the natural inclinations originating from it… considered in themselves natural inclinations are good, i.e. not reprehensible, and to want to extirpate them would not only be futile but harmful and blameworthy as well” (Religion, 81-102). Does Kant not thereby contradict his earlier comments on the nature of inclinations? I would like to suggest in this essay that this “contradiction” is the result of a significant theoretical development that Kant makes in the Religion: the doctrine of radical evil. That is, there is a shift in his thinking concerning theodicy. I will also attempt to situate this shift in the broader context of Kant’s penchant to secularize various theological precepts. Lastly, I will show the implications of this theoretical development for Kant&amp;rsquo;s thinking about the formation of an ethical community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no doubt that both the negative assessment of inclinations in the Groundwork and their more sanguine appraisal in the Religion have significant theodical implications. For in both cases, the question of God’s relationship to the manifest evil in the world necessarily arises. In Kant’s first formulation, one&amp;rsquo;s ability to act morally, that is, according to practical reason,  is hindered by one&amp;rsquo;s inclinations. It is his ability to act according to the moral law that distinguishes man; he is, then, essentially predisposed to goodness: he is a being “that has reason and a will” (Groundwork, 19). That man is endowed with a practical faculty whose function is to “produce a will that is good”, means that any evil that man commits cannot be attributed to his practical faculty (Groundwork, 21). Put in theological terms, God, “as the highest good”, has created man as predisposed to good rather than evil (Groundwork, 47). What, then, is the source of evil if it does not naturally inhere in man, i.e., he does not have an  “implanted natural instinct” to evil (Groundwork, 21)? Kant argues that it is by neglecting, rather than cultivating his natural disposition that man is led astray.  That is, in the Groundwork, Kant does not think that man is endowed with a secondary predisposition, as it were, that opposes his predisposition to good. Inclinations  are immanent to our natural predisposition; they are a product of our constitutive limitedness. Kant writes that “the cultivation of reason… in many ways limits… the attainment… of happiness” (Groundwork, 21). This indicates that one must perfect or cultivate one&amp;rsquo;s reason, or predisposition to good; it is the failure to do so that allows one to become overcome with a profusion of inclinations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there is a significant problem with this formulation, one which Kant identifies in “On the Miscarriage of all Philosophical Trials at Theodicy (hereafter, “Miscarriage”): “[since] no guilt can be ascribed to God…the ground of this ill… must inevitably be sought in the essence of things, specifically in the necessary limitations of humanity as a finite nature; hence the latter can also not be held responsible for it” (Miscarriage, 27). Essentially, this first formulation leads to an insurmountable conceptual impasse— if evil cannot be ascribed to God or our inclinations (to put the blame on our inclinations actually absolves us of our wrong-doings), then what is the origin of evil? It is in the Religion that Kant gives his answer to this question. He does so by positing the existence of a predisposition to evil in human beings. That man has this propensity to evil does not mean that now the blame can be placed on God; to do so would be to prematurely give up on this subtle re-formulation of Kant’s theodicy. That is, one cannot understand this propensity to evil as one that was placed in man by God. It is brought about entirely by man himself. One should not therefore understand by the term propensity or predisposition that a “natural impulse” to evil exists within man (Religion, 70).
Evil, rather, has its source in the radical freedom that constitutes man&amp;rsquo;s being in the world.  If one were to “naturalize” this freedom then “the entire exercise of freedom could be traced back to a determination through natural causes— and this would contradict freedom” (Religion, 71). As Kant goes on to write, when one speaks of the propensity to evil or good— that the human being is “by nature good… or… evil” — what is meant is that he himself is the “first ground” of his actions (Religion, 71). It is thus only with this “doctrine of evil” that man himself is  held entirely accountable for his actions, and consequently, evil. Whereas in the earlier formulation man was characterized as essentially limited, he is now made to stand before the infinite abyss of freedom. There is another sense in which the “innateness” of evil ought to be qualified. That evil is innate does not mean that every human being is unreservedly evil but that any case or instance in which an individual acts immorally can be attributed to this propensity. As Kant writes, “we may presuppose evil as subjectively necessary in every human being, even the best” — the “supreme subjective ground” of evil is rooted in humanity itself (Religion, 80). To attribute it to this propensity however is not the same as attributing it to inclinations because the former acknowledges the individual as cause but the latter does not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is yet another reason for Kant’s re-formulation in the Religion. Kant writes, “[h]owever those valiant men [the Stoics] mistook their enemy, who is not to be sought in the natural inclinations… We have to wrestle not against flesh and blood… but against principalities and powers, against evil spirits” (Religion, 103). At first glance, this appears to be an entirely uncharacteristic argument from Kant; it is as though he is appealing to the suprasensible to ground his argument. However, this is not the case. Kant makes this argument only to privilege practical reason over theoretical reason when it comes to assessing the origins of  evil. If evil is innate then it cannot be subject to an empirical investigation. Kant’s argument, then, does not seek to “extend our cognition beyond the world” (Religion, 103). The concept of evil here has a similar status to the concepts of God, the soul, or the afterlife in the sense that they are made available only for practical use. Kant’s invocation of concepts that are usually associated with theology is an attempt to establish “over against biblical theology… a philosophical theology” (Religion, 61). Kant is not a biblical exegete but nor does he straightforwardly reject these categories. This also applies to his views of theodicy: the theodicy he elaborates cannot be interpreted as a simple continuation of orthodox, or doctrinal theodicies, but is rather what Kant calls an authentic theodicy (a distinction that he makes in the “Miscarriage”, but that is further developed in Religion). Significantly, Kant argues that this authentic theodicy, far from being his own invention, can be gleaned from Scripture itself, as is seen in his reading of the Book of Job. This is similar to his argument in Religion that every religion contains a “moral doctrine intelligible to all human beings”; indeed the moral religion predates all faiths, lying “hidden in human reason” (Religion, 143). A scriptural scholar is concerned more so with exegesis, and thus emphasizes the doctrinal aspects of Scripture; he is the representative of ecclesiastical faith. The universal moral religion that Kant speaks of, however, has as its expositor none other than the “religion of reason”  (Religion, 145).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is at this point that Kant begins discussion of the conditions necessary for the “church universal” that supersedes ecclesiastical faith. It is important to note that the concept of a universal church, the veritable Kingdom of God, is itself a notable theoretical development that can only be understood in the light of the transition from the theodicy that Kant articulates in the Groundwork to the one found in Religion. As Matthew Rukgaber argues in “The Implied Theodicy of Kant’s Religion within the Boundaries of Mere Reason”, “[p]rior to the solution given in [Religion], Kant’s response to evil was essentially Leibniz’s Fatum Christianum (Christian Fatalism) … [that] we should be content with providence and follow the moral law” (Rukgaber, 215). This is a point of view that is advanced even in the “Miscarriage” through its discussion of the Book of Job: one ought to resign oneself to the way things are and can only hope that God, in His wisdom, will improve things. The “highest good”, Kant argues prior to the publication of Religion, cannot be reached in this life (Rukgaber, 215).  However, Religion is a major departure from this position since it argues that this highest good can materialize in our worldly existence. This can only be realized within an ethical community wherein all of its inhabitants, as Kant writes in a dense footnote, “make[s] the highest possible good in the world his own final end (Religion, 59). It is in the Kingdom of God that all persons, of their own volition, adhere to the “pure reason in the law”, even if in doing so, they do not attain happiness or the promise of a better life in the hereafter (Religion, 60). The ethical community does not only help cultivate this moral nature but also symbolizes it. Kant writes that the “acceptance of the existence of this lawgiver means more than the mere possibility of this object… a proposition that exceeds the concept of the duties of this world” (Religion, 59). That there is an excess here requires an ethical community, since the moral law is generally associated with the individual. It is only within such a community, then, that moral progress is possible. At the same time, however, this excess precludes finality; one can say only of this moral progress that it is to carry on indefinitely, that it is a “never fully attainable ideal” (Religion, 135). Yet, Kant prohibits the “people of God” to remain idle in the face of this fact, or to resign themselves to the will of God since it is only Him, and not human beings that can establish the Kingdom (Religion, 135). Herein resides the ethical kernel of Kant’s formulation. Whereas in ecclesiastical terms, the moral father is visible and the one to whom all inhabitants are to wholly submit, for Kant the moral father is invisible— for the people of God to  honor him is for them to  enter into a “free, universal and enduring union of hearts” (Religion, 136). What is emphasized is not God as such but his practical necessity i.e., His role in facilitating this union. And ultimately it is precisely this affectionate union that is the only adequate response to the presence of evil in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;works-cited&#34;&gt;Works Cited&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kant, Immanuel, et al. Groundwork of the Metaphysics of Morals: A German-English Edition.Cambridge University Press, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kant, Immanuel, et al. Religion and Rational Theology. Cambridge University Press, 2006.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kant, Immanuel, et al. Religion within the Boundaries of Mere Reason and Other Writings. Cambridge University Press, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rukgaber, Matthew. “The Implied Theodicy of Kant’s Religion within the Boundaries of Mere Reason: Love as a Response to Radical Evil.” International Journal for Philosophy of Religion, vol. 85, no. 2, 2019, pp. 213–33. JSTOR, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/48700497&#34;&gt;https://www.jstor.org/stable/48700497&lt;/a&gt;. Accessed 14 Apr. 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nietzsche and the Sovereign Individual</title>
      <link>/posts/deleuze/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jun 2023 13:58:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/deleuze/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Writes Martha Nussbaum, in Hiding from Humanity, that “the fantasy of self-transcendence… is all too likely to be a fantasy of impossible strength or purity, in which crucial elements of the human are lacking” (Nussbaum, 106). She takes Nietzsche’s moral philosophy to be exemplative of this fantasy, arguing in a footnote that Nietzsche conceives of an “impossible “overman” who lacks typical weaknesses” as the end-goal of all moral striving (Nussbaum, 362). It is important here to make a terminological distinction, as I believe Nussbaum errs in referring to an individual who “lacks typical weaknesses” as the overman. Nietzsche’s construction of the overman occurs at an ontological rather than individual level. To identify the overman with the elimination of certain human weaknesses, then, is an egregious misreading, since it leads us to understand certain concepts, such as the will-to-power, as a process whereby one individual, lacking “typical weaknesses”, violently exerts physical force over another.  No doubt the concept of the will-to-power has something to do with forces, but, as mentioned above, these forces are to be understood ontologically. As Gilles Deleuze argues in Nietzsche and Philosophy, the will to power refers not “to an individual, to a person, but rather to an event, that is to the forces in their various relationships in a proposition or a phenomenon (Deleuze, xi).  The discharge of strength that Nietzsche believes is necessary for the proper functioning of all living creatures should not be understood solely as the discharge of physical force (which, for Nietzsche, is the lowest, most base expression of the will to power) but also one that is, in its most sublime expression, creative : “Genuine philosophers… are commanders and legislators… their creating is legislating, their will to truth is— will to power (Nietzsche, 136). Thus the overman cannot be thought of simply as an invulnerable Stoic, since “he is the… product of the will to power”; he is beholden not to a brutish ethical ideal, but to a creative process of becoming (Deleuze, xii). A Nietzschean concept that would have been more appropriate to use in this context would have been that of the  “sovereign individual” (hereafter, SI), since Nietzsche seems to understand the SI as a model for self-mastery. The SI, then, can be understood at a personal, or individual level rather than an ontological one. But even if this correction were made, and we understood  the SI as representing “impossible strength or purity”, Nussbaum would yet again err in supposing that the SI is, for Nietzsche, a positive ethical ideal. In this essay, I will argue that Nietzsche does not understand the SI to be an ideal, prophet-like figure worthy of emulation. He considers the SI to be worthy of the most serious condemnation and mockery— for Nietzsche, the SI is a product, not an undoing of, the ascetic ideal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent scholarship has cast doubt on the idea that Nietzsche had a positive ethical ideal at all. Given his fiercely polemical style and critical deftness, with which he deconstructs various value-systems,  it might come as a surprise that Nietzsche does not offer his readers a “way forward”, so to speak, or an alternative value system. This refusal to give guidance, however, is constitutive of his philosophy as such.  When, for example, Zarathustra is asked if there is a certain way one ought to live one&amp;rsquo;s life, his response is that no such way exists. Brian Leiter argues that while Nietzsche “aims at freeing higher human beings from their false consciousness about morality”,  his philosophy is unconcerned with “a transformation of society at large” (Leiter, SEP). The concept of false consciousness here should not be taken to mean that an individual is deceived by certain social mores which can be overcome through a (philosophical or otherwise) corrective, yielding a fundamental truth. Rather, false consciousness means that the standpoint of modern consciousness is false; Nietzsche “look[s] upon the whole of consciousness primarily as “false” consciousness” (Ricoeur, 33). This is precisely why it is  impossible to speak of a Nietzschean moral philosophy, if by moral philosophy we mean a set of edifying, instructive propositions that determine how one ought to live one&amp;rsquo;s life. Nussbaum’s political liberalism, on the other hand, requires that  “certain basic rights and liberties for all citizens” are valued (Nussbaum, 62). Moreover, she identifies “primary goods”, that are, ostensibly, “prerequisites for leading a flourishing life” (Nussbaum, 62). The subject, then, for Nussbaum, is considered only in relation to the positive ethical ideals of liberalism; just institutions produce the liberal subject, and in turn, “require support from the psychology of [these] citizens” (Nussbaum, 16). The subject is conceived in an entirely different way in Nietzsche’s philosophy. Prior to an investigation of the role of the SI in the Genealogy and Nietzsche’s views on morality, one must confront the Nietzschean subject. The subject, for Nietzsche, is a multiplicity and cannot be understood independently of the will to power. (Nietzsche, 490). The subject is non-substantial, nor is it a unity. It does not possess any essential or innate characteristics in Nietzsche&amp;rsquo;s ontology— he heralds the death of the subject in the same breath that he exclaims “God is dead!”. The subject is a fabrication because it is a name that is (in a manner that is not metaphysically justifiable) added on to a “profusion of competing wills to power” (Booth, 121). It cannot play any regulative role whatsoever. Such a conception of the subject calls into question the possibility of ever arriving at absolute truth. If the subject is fabricated, a mere convention that has social rather than natural origins, then the same thing can be said of the truth. Truth is nothing but a “uniformly valid and binding designation… for things” inaugurated under contingent circumstances (Nietzsche, 354) Both the subject and the truth are then, for Nietzsche, impermanent. The Nietzschean riposte to Nussbaum’s argument that the precepts of liberalism, even if not universally true or valid, can be argued to be superior to various other socio-political arrangements (such as communitarianism) through an impartial investigative procedure, would be that this procedure would be carried out not by a rational agent, but by a “self-deceiving subject” that assumes the truth of what it is attempting to demonstrate as true. As David Booth argues in “Nietzsche on the “Subject as Multiplicity”, the subject “is able to fabricate religious ideals and “other worlds” … without necessarily having any consciousness of its authorship of those ideals or words”,  and instead posits them as universal truths awaiting discovery (Booth, 121). In the second treatise of the Genealogy, Nietzsche argues that such an investigative procedure, far from being impartial, is one that is essentially “ascetic”, whereby “few ideas are to be made indelible, omnipresent, unforgettable, “fixed”&amp;hellip; and the ascetic procedures… are means for taking these ideas out of competition with all other ideas” (Nietzsche, 38).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the treatise, Nietzsche refers to the SI as the “ripest fruit” of a certain process— but what is this process? It might seem at first as a critical break from the morality of custom; Nietzsche’s discussion of the SI seems almost laudatory, devoid of his usual cynicism. The SI, however, is the “ripest fruit” on a tree whose roots are poisonous (Nietzsche, 37). When discussing the SI, Nietzsche’s tone is not laudatory, but rather bitterly ironic and derisive. The SI emerges from a process which has made man calculable, in fact it is the “great justification” of the morality of custom (Nietzsche, 36). But despite Nietzsche placing the SI at the end of this monstrous, “prehistoric” process, does his discussion of the matter not seemingly take an abrupt turn in the pages that follow (Nietzsche, 36)? Is the SI not constituted through a negation of the morality of custom, embodying a higher, more perfect ideal, possessing his “own independent long will”; the SI, writes Nietzsche is an  “autonomous and supermoral” agent, “resembling only himself” (we know already that Nietzsche does not allow for a self-identical subject) (Nietzsche, 36). One could say that the morality of custom is the SI’s constitutive negation; the SI cannot be conceived of as truly “free… from the morality of custom” since even to negate, or overcome, the morality of custom is, in some sense, to be tied to it.  Recall Nietzsche’s views on false consciousness: it is the greatest folly to think that one can pierce this veil in order to apprehend “reality”. That is, if Nietzsche truly praised the SI, it would mean that he viewed false consciousness as a state of affairs to be remedied or improved upon, which, as I have argued above, is not the case.  But this is what modern man—the SI—strives towards, and it is precisely for this reason that he is an object of scorn for Nietzsche.
That the SI is indelibly marked by the morality of custom becomes especially evident when one considers the relationship between memory and promise-making that Nietzsche details in the second treatise. The SI is that individual who is “permitted to promise”, but this ability to make promises does not signal a break from humanity qua herd but actually constitutes it: “one has given one’s promise in order to live within the advantages of society, — and truly!&amp;hellip; one finally came “to reason”&amp;hellip; how much blood and horror there is at the base of all “good things”!” (Nietzsche, 36). If one were up to this point unconvinced that Nietzsche, in referring to the SI as “autonomous and supermoral”, does so in an entirely ironic manner, this passage makes it clear that he could not have meant it otherwise. For even the most hallowed faculty of man— reason— is here subject to ridicule. The SI’s “mastery over… affects”, awe-inspiring “seriousness”, is founded on “blood and horror” (Nietzsche, 38, 39).  Nietzsche is explicit on this point— all of these “good things” and qualities are in fact the culmination of, and thus belong in their entirety to “asceticism” (Nietzsche, 38, 39). If Nietzsche distinguishes between the SI and the herd, it is only to the extent that the SI remains within the herd, unlike its other members, without the threat of external punishment— “it has [thoroughly] internalized the process” (Rukgaber, 216). The SI is thus an individual who self-flagellates; he becomes his own executioner. He may very well avoid the slave morality that characterizes the herd, but he does so only superficially, since the instinct the SI internalizes— what he calls his “conscience”— is slave morality under a different name. This conscience, far from being something naturally present in man, surfaces at the same time as “contract law”, the debtor-creditor relationship, and such concepts as “guilt… duty… sacred duty” (Rukgaber, 230; Nietzsche, 41). The SI can indeed be said to be a superior being, with a major caveat: he is superior only to those weaker, less able beings in the herd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This reading can be contested on two counts. One may argue that the SI is Nietzsche’s positive ethical ideal simply because of his affirmative power— the SI is capable of saying “yes” to himself (he is a responsible being) and this puts him outside the herd. Secondly, one could object to the evolutionary picture provided by arguing that the SI represents a “unique form of agency” that develops “out of animality”, and is for this reason fully “outside” the herd (Rukgaber, 217). I will invoke Deleuze to respond to the first objection. He writes in Nietzsche and Philosophy that “[t]o affirm is not to take responsibility for, to take on the burden of what is, but to release, to set free what lives” (Deleuze, 185). As mentioned before, according to Deleuze, true affirmation must be exhaustively creative; a certain kind of inventiveness that is absent in merely “taking responsibility”. We cannot oppose the SI to the self-denying, weak-willed ascetic since the SI’s “yes” is not affirmative in the sense that Nietzsche wants us to think about affirmation. According to Deleuze, the SI’s affirmative power is similar to that of an ass— “the ass is the animal that says “Ye-a”, the affirmative and affirming animal” (Deleuze, 170). The SI, like the ass, affirms only the negative; it does not say yes to affirmation itself but only the “nihilistic reality of the ‘no’” (de Zeeuw, 7). What is in fact an impulse hostile to life deceivingly presents itself as affirmative.  There is a basic interpretative error that the second objection relies on. It assumes that Nietzsche is offering the reader an account of the evolution of the human from animality, or human agency out of animal-like instinct. But the SI evolves out of “already human capacities” that function as the ground for its conscience (Rukgaber, 217). Take for example what Nietzsche writes about forgetfulness in the second treatise: “[a]nd precisely this necessarily forgetful animal, in whom forgetting is a strength… has bred for himself a counter-device, memory, with the help of which forgetfulness can be suspended in certain cases” (Nietzsche, 36). One should not be fooled by the word “animal” here, since Nietzsche is referring to human beings at a certain stage of their development; the ability to suspend forgetfulness is, of course, preceded by forgetfulness, which is still a “uniquely human [capacity]” (Rukgaber, 217). While this development concerns the coming to birth of ethical agency, it does not emerge out of “mere animality” — the question that Nietzsche asks is not how consciousness develops in the animal mind but how the subject comes to be what it is, or, as Richard Schacht argues, how human beings develop a (modern) personal identity (Rukgaber, 219). The second part of this objection concerns the SI’s self-imposed exile from the herd. While I have argued above that the SI cannot be outside the herd, it is also important to note that, if one could attribute to Nietzsche a positive ethical ideal, he would never conceive of it along the lines of an autonomous agent completely detached from mundane, worldly affairs. If a Nietzschean ethical ideal could be described in any meaningful sense, it would be exemplified not by a being who transcends the world but one who immerses himself in it, “[burying] himself within nature” in a redemptive manner (Rukgaber, 229).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no doubt that Nietzsche is a masterful ironist, writing with a doubleness of tone that is purposefully confounding and misleading. Yet this should not be mistaken for a philosophical error since it is a question of style, which is part and parcel of his philosophy. If one were to attempt to “see through” Nietzsche’s various idiosyncrasies, in order to distill his thought, arrive at its “essence”, one would find that no such thing exists. He uplifts in the same breath that he debases; he offers “not one Truth but many experiences and many truths” (Ansell-Pearson, 314). Hence we should not be surprised that Nietzsche is able to maintain two seemingly contradictory positions, as appears to be the case with the SI (though I think I have demonstrated in this essay that Nietzsche only apparently praises the SI and harbors for this product of asceticism the deepest loathing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;works-cited&#34;&gt;Works Cited&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deleuze, Gilles. Nietzsche and Philosophy. Bloomsbury, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ricœur, Paul. Freud and Philosophy. Yale University Press, 1970.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nietzsche, Friedrich Wilhelm, and Horace B. Samuel. On the Genealogy of Morality: The Three Essays Complete with Notes. Adansonia Press, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ansell-Pearson, Keith. “Who Is the Ubermensch? Time, Truth, and Woman in Nietzsche.” Journal of the History of Ideas, vol. 53, no. 2, 1992, pp. 309–31. JSTOR, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.2307/2709876&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.2307/2709876&lt;/a&gt;. Accessed 17 Jan. 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew Rukgaber. “The ‘Sovereign Individual’ and the ‘Ascetic Ideal’: On a Perennial Misreading of the Second Essay of Nietzsche’s On the Genealogy of Morality.” Journal of Nietzsche Studies, vol. 43, no. 2, 2012, pp. 213–39. JSTOR, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5325/jnietstud.43.2.0213&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5325/jnietstud.43.2.0213&lt;/a&gt;. Accessed 17 Jan. 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;De Zeeuw, Daniel. “On Nietzsche’s sovereign individual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Booth, D. Nietzsche on “the subject as multiplicity”. Man and World 18, 121–146 (1985). &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/BF01248611&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/BF01248611&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leiter, Brian, &amp;ldquo;Nietzsche’s Moral and Political Philosophy&amp;rdquo;, The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy (Summer 2021 Edition), Edward N. Zalta (ed.), URL = &lt;a href=&#34;https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/sum2021/entries/nietzsche-moral-political/&#34;&gt;https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/sum2021/entries/nietzsche-moral-political/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nussbaum, Martha C. Hiding from Humanity Disgust, Shame, and the Law. Princeton University Press, 2009.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Krause</title>
      <link>/posts/krause/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2023 13:55:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/krause/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“The public sphere is for us a process of production rather than an object that pre-exists and that you can then cater to with your own output… counter-public for us is a process of igniting solidarity among people who might otherwise have very different ideas…The bourgeois public sphere, in contrast, is something like a pre-given foil” (Krause, 121). The concept of the public that Negt proposes here is one that is continually produced, but this production is not a homogenizing force. A counter-public is not produced by subsuming various, perhaps marginalized, identities under a general category. It is less a production of yet another “group” than it is an attempt to create relationships, engender solidarity amongst groups that, superficially, do not resemble one another. It seems that Negt is opposing the Kantian conception of the public, specifically in his repudiation of the “bourgeois public sphere”. Kant&amp;rsquo;s notion of the public sphere presupposes a bourgeois, that is “individualist and rationalist”, subject (Krause, 119). The public sphere, for Kant, is always already in relation to the private, despite the distinction between the two. One cannot betray one&amp;rsquo;s civic duties, one&amp;rsquo;s responsibility towards one&amp;rsquo;s work. So it is clear that the private sphere is “pre-given” in the sense that Negt uses the word. But is the public sphere any less restrictive? It is only the scholar who has any substantive authority in this sphere, catering to the public with his own output. Negt, on the other hand, calls for an expansion of the “concept of interests” that belongs not only to scholars, but to workers— “They  need  to extend  their  concept  of  work,  the  concept  of  interests,  of  their  political mandate, their cultural mandate, which means they need to develop more than workplace interests (Krause, 125). What is especially important in Negt’s formulation is that it avoids romanticizing the worker: the worker is not primally innocent, he is responsible not only to himself and his comrades, but to members of society outside the trade union.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This disturbed balance between ‘is’ and ‘ought’, the hegemony of being” (Krause, 123).  Krause here touches on a problem that is constitutively important for political theory. What can a people hope for? Can the “hegemony of being” which in our contemporary context, must be understood as the hegemony of capitalism be disrupted? Negt seems to resist the idea of a unilateral revolution and the naive notion that one can use a “single point” to somehow “unhinge the whole system” (Krause, 123). There is no Archimedean point— there is a multitude of them in the same sense that there is no public, only (counter) publics. This is again opposed to the idea of obedience that is espoused by Kant, one that refuses to engage with the concept of revolution.
“Because the pressure not only to look intelligent but also to say intelligent things has put students under so much stress” (Krause, 124). I wholeheartedly agree with this sentiment, but this is something that is probably very difficult to get right. For example, how is a professor to ensure this “silent anonymity” while also ensuring that a student is engaged in an “intensive process of learning” rather than merely “appropriating contents”? (Krause, 125).
“The problem in Iraq, just like in Afghanistan, is that as long as production is not built up to a level that can compete in the world market, it will never be a land  capable  of  peace,  even  if  soldiers  remain  there  for  200  years” (Krause, 127).  A shocking conclusion to an otherwise great interview. Who is responsible, in this discussion, of defining peace? Is Iraq and Afghanistan in disarray because of their inability to produce according to demands of the world-market, or is it precisely the demands of the world-market that Negt suggest Iraq and Afghanistan acquiesce to, the root of their problems? This is a market that can only exist if there exists countries that are structurally subservient to it; it is not one that grants sovereignty to those countries that meet its demands.  This point is made all the more incoherent when one considers that it is  completely antithetical to the spirit of a counter-public— are counter-publics fully realized when they become international servants of capital? Then the prefix “counter” is not really needed. Negt also argues that the problem with capitalism is that it cannot produce its own competition— as though the structural crises endemic to capitalism would disappear once the playing field were leveled, as it were. This is made all the more ironic given Negt’s preoccupation with the “hegemony of being” and his attempt to avoid reproducing this hegemony.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review of &#39;The Physicists&#39;</title>
      <link>/posts/durrenmatt/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 13:24:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/durrenmatt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One’s initial impression reading The Physicists, especially before the reader is made aware of the true identities of the three inmates, could be that these venerable men (Möbius in particular)  are no longer capable of pursuing scientific research due to their falling victim to religious delusion, or some other form of irrationalism that hinders their creative abilities. But it is revealed at the end of the play that all of the men are sound of mind, in fact, Möbius is so brilliant a physicist that the other two men want to use him for their own purposes. Newton is representative of a science that distances itself from politics; it sees itself as above the trifles and banalities that constitute the average everyday existence of humankind. Einstein’s is a science that is beholden to the politics of the nation-state; the scientist is impotent and can only “hope that the party will follow [his] recommendations, nothing more” (Dürrenmatt, 79). There is, however, no real difference between these two positions as Möbius notes, “[e]ach of you is trying to palm off a different theory, yet the reality you offer me is the same in both cases: a prison” (Dürrenmatt, 80). And what is this thing that both elevates and at the same time debases humankind? For Möbius, it is something monstrous and traumatizing, hence the eschatological themes that pervade the play. This is also why Möbius’ faked delusions are religious in nature: it is only in the mythology of religion that Möbius finds adequate concepts and images to help “make sense” of the formidable meaninglessness of scientific inquiry. Mobius’ “Song of Solomon” makes it clear that there is no “end-goal” to scientific inquiry (“Toward a few white stars/That we never reach anyhow) and how it is a process that is ridden with errors (“We had long since mistaken the sun for Sirius”) (Dürrenmatt, 44).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prophethood is not an honored vocation. One is dismissed, ridiculed, and met with the most extreme violence for the truths that one tells to a people who do not want to hear it, or are threatened by it. This might have been the case for the prophets of old, a modern- day prophet is harmless; he is similar to a court jester. He need not be exiled, he can be sent to an asylum to be cured of his pathology. But if Möbius is a “prophet” (or a madman— it makes no difference) it is not because he is divinely inspired (he does not actually see King Solomon) but rather because he directly confronts and acknowledges this disorienting meaninglessness that is at the core of scientific inquiry.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is the Yeshiva Obsolete?</title>
      <link>/posts/grade/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2023 22:05:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/grade/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It appears at times that what is meant by modernism— a vague, almost vacuous term if not contextualized properly— is that period in human history characterized by the alienation of Man. Rapid industrial development and various technological innovations have provided society with those tools that are necessary for it to take seriously the Kantian exhortation that we ought to emerge from our state of self-incurred immaturity. Yet these modern developments are simultaneously instruments of destruction, subjugation, and indeed, alienation. I am not concerned, in this essay, with the Marxian concept of alienation as the estrangement of the laborer from the fruits of his labor, but rather, alienation understood in a more existential sense; as displacement, spiritual impoverishment, and cultural and religious fragmentation. What, then, should we make of this sense of loss? Is our only hope to return assiduously to religious systems of meaning, refusing the cynical realism of modernity? Or do the world-historical catastrophes set in motion by modernity— the Shoah, in particular— allow us to rethink such concepts as God, history, and man? More concretely, what is the role of religious institutions, such as the Yeshiva, in the modern world? Are they merely the vestiges of premodernity, attempting to resuscitate a religious world-view experiencing its death throes, or can they help us navigate the modern world? My Quarrel with Hersh Rayner is concerned with precisely this tension. The complexity of this tension or antagonism defies a simple resolution and it is for this reason that I will argue that the representation of the Yeshiva in My Quarrel is marked by a certain ambivalence; it does not straightforwardly identify the Yeshiva with ideal piety, nor is it a paean dedicated to the glorification of the supposedly redemptive qualities of modernity. I will argue that while there exists a fundamental incongruence between Chaim and Hersh’s positions, it is this incongruence, this antagonism, that is the very condition of possibility for their debate to unfold. If we understand Chaim’s position not as a rejection of Jewish theology, but rather one that has immense religious significance, it can be argued that both characters are, in the final analysis, grappling with the same problems and questions, despite offering different solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an urgent, perhaps even dangerous, question that can be posed upon finishing My Quarrel: is it possible to take seriously the antagonism that is constitutive of Jewish study and identity if this antagonism calls into question the study of Torah, or some other fundamental tenet of Jewish theology itself? Even in the fiercest of disagreements what is always presupposed is that one begins from the Torah. It is from this starting point that interpretive differences may abound. What is to be done when this ground is demolished? Given the radicality of this proposition, one may, like Hersh, reject it a priori. However, this rejection would imply that Chaim’s position— his concerns and questions— have a purely secular import and are unintelligible when applied to religious discourse. This is far from the case. If Chaim retorts that the first question Hersh addresses to him is unintelligible— “Your question, Hersh Rasseyner, is no question at all. I do what I have to do”— it is not because he rejects Jewish spirituality in toto but recognizes that spirituality, in a modern context, must be re-imagined ( not re-jected) (Grade 24). Indeed, Chaim is entirely critical of the developments of modernity which he sees as initiating a crisis within Judaism. Addressing Hersh’s accusations, he solemnly proclaims that “You don’t understand that I myself say ‘No’ to the world as it is. And yet I force myself to say ‘Yes’ because I believe in my street” (Grade 25). The “as it is” is of crucial importance and is indicative of Chaim’s firm belief that a world-view that espouses a sort of radical asceticism is seldom helpful in navigating the treacherous terrain of modernity. If the alienation of the subject is constitutive of modernity, then what good can possibly come from a withdrawal from the world? Should not the duty of the Rebbe be to foster meaningful relationships with the “the porters with their backs broken from carrying their loads; the artisans sweating at their workbenches” (Grade 25)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is thus a dialectical tension between Chaim’s ‘Yes’ and ‘No’ — declarations both of affirmation and negation— that allow him to navigate not only the modern world, but Jewishness itself. Notice how Hersh refuses even the possibility of affirmation, collapsing this dialectic— in a manner befitting his misanthropic disposition, he defines Jewishness negatively, “I have heard that your pamphlet, your excuse for a book, is called Yes. But I tell you, ‘No!’” (Grade 24). In a sense, then, Chaim is even more of a “traditional” Jew than Hersh because he does not disavow this contradiction! Although Hersh believes that Chaim has a phantasmic conception of Judaism, one must take seriously Chaim’s  rejoinder that it is Hersh who has “dreamed up a world and then renounced it” (Grade 31).  I would go even further than Chaim—Hersh has dreamed up an insular conception of Judaism itself. Traditionalism, as is argued by Joseph Katz, can be understood as a modern phenomenon. By expressing a desire to return to an idyllic, supposedly authentic past, those who espouse the most stringent forms of orthodoxy, paradoxically, introduce new content into religious tradition. Indeed, calling upon God to justify His ways, far from being blasphemous, is well-documented in Jewish history. Was it not Job who challenged his Lord by crying out in agony, “If only I knew how to find God, how to enter his court, I would state my case before Him and set out my arguments in full; then I should learn what answer he would give and find out what he had to say” (Job 23:3-5)? Did not Judaism begin with an agreement, a contract between Man and God? There were different methods of teaching even in rabbinic Judaism. Did not Hillel respond to the gentile with a gentle playfulness when he had been rebuked harshly by Shammai beforehand?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As such, this tension persists between their positions, even though Hersh is unable to, or unwilling to acknowledge it. While refusing to acknowledge the religious significance of Chaim’s position, Hersh does not reject the importance of disputations in the history of Judaism— “For you, who are on the outside, Hasidism and Musar are just two opposing points of view… But actually, they both strengthened Judaism and their dispute is long forgotten” (Grade 29). The irony here is, of course, palpable. Hersh’s denigration of Chaim’s position is aimed precisely at the idea that Chaim trivializes Judaism. Concerning the dispute between Hasidism and Musar he says, “If the rabbis once fought over  Hasidism and Musar it was because they were afraid the new path would draw Jews away from strict observance” (Grade 29). But is Chaim not proposing precisely a “new path”?  It is only by preemptively designating Chaim an “outsider” that Hersh is able to evade his well-founded and provocative questions. He considers him to be an individual who “ran away from being Jewish” disguising his “flight with high-sounding phrases” (Grade 43).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chaim, cognizant of the antagonism that has allowed for the development of his own spirituality, is conciliatory rather than dismissive: “As I sat here listening to you, I sometimes thought I was listening to myself” (Grade 47).
Hersh, unbeknownst to himself, reveals that, conceptually, his  “Jewish history” depends on a form of retroactive causation; he canonizes certain disputes in the history of Judaism while refusing to acknowledge the religious significance of his disagreement with Chaim. For Hersh, these were necessary disputes, while Chaim’s grievances are merely contingent.  He can only come to this conclusion retroactively— he does not realize that this “return to the past” is itself an act of interpretation and reordering, and it is only through this temporal reconstruction that he is able to legitimize his own conception of Judaism. It would be unfair, then, to say that Chaim is the sole character in this story concerned with reimagining Judaism. His reimagining disrupts this linear temporality and embraces fully the uncertain and speculative. One can imagine that if Hersh were miraculously transported to a future where Chaim’s position was taken more seriously by Jewish intelligentsia,  he would say of their disagreement the very same thing he now says of the dispute between Musar and Hasidism: “for those who observe and practice Jewishness they are one and the same” (Grade 29).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An investigation into the category of Jewishness must necessarily examine the role of study in producing subjects. Study should not be understood— and this is particularly true of religious study— as the acquisition of information but rather as a process of subjectivation. But the subject is always haunted by the possibility of its demolition or disappearance. This forces those tasked with teaching to confront an unsettling question: what is to be done when this process is disrupted by a historical trauma? If the destruction of the Temple rendered obsolete certain forms of worship, but not Judaism as a whole, then must we take seriously the argument that the Shoah also calls for a &amp;ldquo;re-imagining&amp;rdquo; of Judaism and the Yeshiva? We must keep in mind that this re-imagination is not a wholesale negation of the past, nor is it a simple acquiescence to modernity.  These are questions that are equally difficult both for the traditionalist and the secularist. Even the steadfast Hersh appears to falter when faced with them, bypassing the issue by a perfunctory maneuver: “The almighty helps. What difference does it make how you speak? The main thing is what you speak” (Grade 28). Having first flattened the dialectical relationship between the ‘Yes’ and the ‘No’, Hersh now privileges content over form. But his dismissal of the form of education as that which is merely tangential to the process of subjectivation also reveals the incertitude that plagues him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although  Hersh appears to have ready-made answers to all of Chaim’s queries, a certain anxiety belies his fiery passion. He yearns for the security and sense of wholeness that was once offered by the Yeshiva— “Each of us filed and polished his own soul… Then came the Germans” (Grade 36). Evidently, even Hersh acknowledges that a shift— what Levinas calls a “ruin of representation” — cosmic in its scope, has befallen Judaism and Jewish study. Herein lies the essence of trauma— the subject is forced to reckon with something that is utterly unfamiliar to it but is nonetheless transfixed by it and thus irreversibly changed. Hersh, in the face of the suspension of the symbolic order can only cry out “we want a more onerous code, more commandments, more laws, more prohibitions” — the only way to overcome the threat of the suspension is precisely through this excess.  (Grade 44).  Any change to the structure of the Yeshiva would be seen as a compromise bordering on heresy. Hersh fears that this change would result in a form of study in which “anything goes”, thereby undermining the rigor that is supposed to be constitutive of study. Chaim, however, does not want to trivialize study, nor does he conceive of Jewishness as a superfluous category after the trauma of the Shoah. He tells Hersh that “we, too, are after wholeness, not  a middle-of-the-road compromise” (Grade 48).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this “wholeness” is divided into two disparate parts: “Jewish tradition and secular culture” (Grade 48). It is only by embracing this schism, by “taking on a double responsibility” that a concrete solution might be arrived at. Moreover, Chaim argues that there are structural changes within the Jewish world itself that necessitate a rethinking of study. The fantasy of a self-sufficient Yeshiva no longer exists as the secular encroaches on the religious and every aspect of life is subject to the logic of capital— “So I won’t waste time telling you about the powerful and wealthy Jewish leaders who made the community of Israel into their footstool” (Grade 48). Chaim tells Hersh, “Reb Hesh, let us embrace—” (Grade 53). The dash at the end of the sentence, far from being an editorial mistake or authorial idiosyncrasy , signifies a certain incompleteness, gestures at a new beginning, and is inherently interruptive. It concretizes the speculative import of Chaim’s arguments. This ending is not cathartic, the reader does not witness the interlocutors put aside their differences in order to affirm some Absolute Truth. And yet, the possibility of reconciliation remains amidst the strife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;works-cited&#34;&gt;Works Cited&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grade, Chaim, and Herbert H. Paper. &amp;ldquo;My Quarrel with Hersh Rasseyner&amp;rdquo;. 1982.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fanon and the Politics of Desire</title>
      <link>/posts/psychoanalysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2023 15:11:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/psychoanalysis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;[The] uncanny foreignness is within us: we are our own foreigners, we are divided&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;                    — Julia Kristeva, Strangers to Ourselves
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the crucial insights of psychoanalysis is that the dead, or the forgotten past, have a claim on us— their  presence can often be felt more viscerally than the undead—that which is alive and presents itself to us directly in physical and psychical reality.  This is an observation unnerving as it is profound, as it unsettles, indeed disfigures, the supposedly rationalistic ethos constitutive of modernity. Psychoanalytic theory is especially well-suited in dealing with the spectral since its very condition of possibility is grounded in its oblique confrontation with that which otherwise might be dismissed as mere fantasy. Moreover, the fundamental theoretical object of psychoanalysis— the unconscious— possesses this spectral, phantom-like quality.  In my essay, I will be working with the definition of phantom offered by Nicolas Abraham in “Notes on the Phantom” — precisely because he locates the origin of the phantom within the unconscious— in which he theorizes that “the phantom is a formation of the unconscious that has never been conscious… it works like a ventriloquist, like a stranger within the subject’s own mental topography” (Abraham 290).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is not the phantom, then, the uncanny par excellence? The phantom is representative of the excesses of subjectivity, as Dimitris Vardoulakis argues, it “undoes any explication of subjectivity in terms of sharp demarcations” (Vardoulakis 101). It’s emergence relies on some form of familial transmission, it is informed by a “psycho-genetic heritage”, to use Durban’s terminology, yet it is not reducible to this transmission and thus evades ones straight-forward identification with it— one cannot make sense of it through reference to an established “system of relationships” since its primary task is to undo, render unintelligible systems of meaning. I will attend specifically to the role a phantom might have in the formation of the subjective constitution of colonized peoples, or, more specifically, the relationship between the unconscious and (colonial) subjectivity. At the heart of any discussion of the subjectivity of the oppressed is the possibility of its determinate negation, that is, the emancipation of the colonized subject from the discursive framework which assigns to him this subject position in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not only a matter of determining the best political action to achieve this emancipation, but also necessitates a theory, or concept of the subject since every political project presupposes one. An urgent question that must be asked, then, is: what is the defining characteristic of colonial subjectivity? One may argue that it possesses a positive, substantial quality—  Blackness, for example, can be imagined as a concrete category with strict demarcations. The idea of emancipation that follows from this interpretation of subjectivity is one that privileges recognition; the phenomenon of racism will disappear once Black people are recognized not as the obscene Other of European civilization, but as equal to white people. However, I will argue that Blackness should instead be conceptualized as the site of a radical negativity, what Fanon calls the “zone of non-being” —  an interpretation that emphasizes the spectral, phantom-like quality of subjectivity. This understanding of the colonial subject does not lead to an impotent political project, but is rather guided by the insight that the desire for recognition from the Master can only arise within the context of colonial relations. To actualize the paradigmatic shift from the “world of being” to the “world of meaning” that Fanon outlines, I will argue that the colonial subject must work through the contradictions of the socio-symbolic order of colonialism (Fanon).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alain Badiou, praising Freud’s discovery of the fundamental structure of desire in his book The Century, writes, “By 1918, as we can see, Freud had already clearly identified a ploy that has been operative ever since, which consists in preferring the articulation of desire and its object back to a meaning that is pre-constituted in culture, mythology, or religion… this is the hermeneutic ploy, and Freud immediately saw it as an insidious negation of his discovery” (Badiou 115). Badiou touches on an issue that is of central importance to my paper— he clearly articulates the impasse, the “hermeneutic ploy” that one encounters when speaking of something as elusive as desire. In short, the question that Badiou poses, which had been asked by Freud before him is: how can one even begin to speak of something that resists symbolization? The phantom can be thought of as a concept that is conjured precisely in order to grasp this question. And while Badiou here is referring to Freud’s explication of sexual desire, the same question can be asked of the desire to know, or represent, a racialized Other (in this case it is the racialized Other that resists symbolization).  One should not understand Abraham’s use of the word “phantom”, however, as an effort to symbolize the unsymbolizable; he does not attempt to prematurely overcome this impasse or pretend to untangle the psychoanalytic knot.  The phantom exists as a “metapsychological fact” not because it can be identified with an object in phenomenal experience, nor even the loss or lack of this object; instead,  it is founded on a lack of lack, the break-down of symbolic reality as such. (Abraham 171). The phantom exists only as the “gaps” — the unsymbolizable par excellence— “left within us by the secrets of others” (Abraham 171).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phantom, then, is capable of  denaturalizing subjectivity because it reveals these gaps; it disrupts the fantasy of an identity prior to a socially specific signifying process. This is a fantasy that is foundational to the racist, colonial socio-symbolic order since whiteness is conceived as a master-signifier within it. Durban’s discussion of “shadows, ghosts, and chimaeras” is similar to Abraham’s “phantom” in that it too problematizes this idea of  subjectivity as a pre-given, natural category. Recounting a patient&amp;rsquo;s extraordinary psychic development, Durban writes, “At first there was a white hole… White was in white…Then I was in the black hole, screaming and screaming but no one heard” (Durban). One may be quick to dismiss this account as an instantiation of psychic pathology, but what it actually does is provide a model for subjective development. Subjectivation is a violent process; trauma is constitutive of subjectivity. Durban argues that one confronts trauma retroactively. This confrontation takes the form of appropriating an inapprobiable event, i.e., what is commonly referred to as “making sense” of one&amp;rsquo;s trauma. There is always an excess that cannot be contained, however, and so trauma, or the “phantom” carries out its return, when words, stripped of their “libidinal grounding” are uttered (Abraham 174). This should not be understood in the sense that the mere utterance of these words has a magical effect on those who hear it. Language, or words, here denotes not only verbal speech but rather “any signifying system that is based upon differential relations” (Ghosh 1). Recall Lacan in Seminar XX: “the notion of discourse should be taken as a social link (lien social), founded on language, and thus seems not unrelated to what is specified in linguistics as grammar” (Lacan 17). What Abraham calls “phantasmogenic words” have not only a communicative purpose, but also an impact on the chain of signification (Abraham 176). It is also by understanding language in this way that we can arrive at an adequate concept of “haunting”; this obstinate, persistent presence of the phantom and its generational transmission. Subjective traumas of the past, the destruction of a collective identity vis a vis a devastating event, can indeed influence, even determine, the subjective constitution of later generations. In Moses and Monotheism for example, Freud grapples with a question of great existential significance— what is it that makes the Jewish people so resilient? Moses, as the archetypal “father-leader” (killed only to come back to haunt his assailants) is elevated to the dignity of the Thing—that unsymbolizable force that nonetheless ties Jewish identity together—whether the Jews are consciously aware of it or not (Frosh 248).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are the subjective repercussions of this rupture, the emergence of the phantom? The existence of the phantom impels us to think of subjectivity as, paradoxically, that which is removed from itself and is never self-identical to itself. Abraham writes, “The phantom is summoned therefore, at the opportune moment, when it is recognized that a gap was transmitted to the subject with the result of barring him or her from the specific introjections he or she would seek at present” (Abraham 174). Of crucial importance here is the “barring” of the subject, yet another reference to Lacan, who represents the barred subject with the matheme “$”. Only when we have this concept of the barred subject can we explicate the relationship between subjectivity and the unconscious, or the phantom which is a formation of the unconscious. Joan Copjec, in her essay “Vampire, Breast-Feeding, and Anxiety,  writes “&amp;hellip; it is necessary to say that the real is absented, to declare its impossibility…[t]he real that is to be negated cannot be represented by a signifier, since the real is, by definition, that which has no adequate signifier” (Copjec 55). Copjec’s insight is crucial for understanding Fanon&amp;rsquo;s suspicion of the existence of a truly  authentic and concrete Black identity. Moreover, Copjec’s analysis of the relationship between subjectivity and the unconscious can also be applied to the relationship between subjectivity and the socio- symbolic order— if Copjec is arguing that the subject differs from itself, then the very same thing can be said of the socio-symbolic order.  Indeed, Fanon’s critical intervention is directed precisely at this relationship. He does not interpret Blackness as merely an Imaginary (in the sense Lacan uses the word) identity grounded in a coherent Symbolic discourse, but rather, Blackness for Fanon represents the “Real of the colony” —  it is that which the colonial socio-symbolic order must safeguard itself from, the “phantom trace which haunts the Symbolic but cannot be adequately approximated by the function of the signifier” (Thakur 631). It is for this reason that Fanon writes that the colonial subject traverses “the crossroads between Nothingness [le Néant] and Infinity [l’Infini]”; the Black subject specifically is the personification of non-being (Fanon 119; Thakur 641). For Fanon, this “non-negated negativity” arises principally from the impossible situation Black people find themselves in: they can either futilely attempt to “become white”  or try to reconnect to an imagined, mythic past (Thakur 612).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice how Copjec, when discussing the real, uses the words “say” and “declare”, essentially tethering it to the domain of language. This might appear counter-intuitive, perhaps even counterproductive— is not the whole aim of Fanon’s critical project to step outside the colonial socio-symbolic order and disavow its language? And how can we speak of the real if we can only pass over it in silence?  Herein lies the importance of immanent critique: the truly radical act is not to reject in toto colonial language, but rather work through its contradictions and limitations. This is particularly important since one cannot merely strip away one&amp;rsquo;s identity, or literally “step outside” the world that defines one&amp;rsquo;s social being. Fanon himself assigns to language a great value— the very first chapter of  Black Skin, White Masks starts with the following statement:  “I ascribe a basic importance to the phenomenon of language. That is why I find it necessary to begin with this subject, which should provide us with one of the elements in the colored man&amp;rsquo;s comprehension of the dimension of the other” (Fanon 17).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What might this immanent critique look like and can the concept of the phantom be invoked when constructing an emancipatory political project? Homi Bhabha, in his influential essay “Of Mimicry and Man: The Ambivalence of Colonial Discourse” argues that the zone of nonbeing theorized by Fanon allows us to rethink identity and its sedimentation— identity no longer needs as its foundation the transcendent, self-identical Idea but is rather developed in an immanent and differential field. If repetition in the colonial socio-symbolic order serves the purpose of sedimenting subjectivity (I act a certain way because I saw my parents doing the same thing) and reproducing social hierarchies; in the zone of non-being, repetition produces phantoms. While for Fanon, imitating or mimicking the colonizer is ultimately unproductive— “when I tried to claim my negritude intellectual as a concept, they snaatched it away from me” — Bhabha argues that mimicry is marked by a carnivalesque quality that parodies the dominant colonial socio-symbolic order; it is a “mode of representation, that marginalizes the monumentality of history, quite simply mocks its power to be a model, that power which supposedly makes it imitable” (Fanon 111; Bhabha 128). Bhabha argues that mimicry necessarily produces excess and slippage, or in other words, a phantom. Once the phantom emerges, it perpetuates this cycle of repetition, as Abraham reminds us, “[f]inally it gives rise to endless repetition and, more often than not eludes rationalization” (Abraham 175). The phantom produced by mimicry refuses colonial representation and concurrently haunts the colonizer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet, the phantom also haunts the colonized— the subject bears the weight of historical injustices on her shoulders. How does one go about exorcizing these phantoms of which we cannot speak? Abraham is almost silent on this matter, ending the essay with the remark that one ought to place “the effects of the phantom in the social realm” (Abraham). It seems as though we have come full circle, running up against the same impasse that we had attempted to overcome: once again, the colonial subject is forced to confront, perhaps even stay within the colonial socio-symbolic order because, as Copjec argues, the subject is the “failure that sustains the symbolic order” (Copjec 54).  The subject is this failure precisely because she can never apprehend the real. How can the symbolic order accommodate this excess, its disavowed phantoms? My essay has largely been a meditation on this question but still (unsurprisingly) one cannot even hope for a definitive answer. But, this, of course, is not a cause for despair. It is precisely the constitutive incapacity of the symbolic order to accommodate all its referents that creates a  “constant gradient of desire, a perpetual reaching out for the pure reality behind representation” (Kirshner).  The subject will ultimately search in vain for this “pure” reality— as Hegel reminds us, there is nothing behind the curtain of appearance except for what we put there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;works-cited&#34;&gt;Works Cited&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bhabha, Homi. “Of Mimicry and Man: The Ambivalence of Colonial Discourse.” October, vol. 28, 1984, pp. 125–33, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.2307/778467&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.2307/778467&lt;/a&gt;. Accessed 17 May 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dimitris Vardoulakis. “The Return of Negation: The Doppelgänger in Freud’s ‘The “Uncanny.”’” SubStance, vol. 35, no. 2, 2006, pp. 100–16, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jstor.org/stable/4152886&#34;&gt;http://www.jstor.org/stable/4152886&lt;/a&gt;. Accessed 17 May 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FROSH, STEPHEN. “Hauntings: Psychoanalysis and Ghostly Transmission.” American Imago, vol. 69, no. 2, 2012, pp. 241–64, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jstor.org/stable/26305019&#34;&gt;http://www.jstor.org/stable/26305019&lt;/a&gt;. Accessed 17 May 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joshua Durban (2011) Shadows, ghosts and chimaeras: On some early modes of handling psycho‐genetic heritage1, The International Journal of Psychoanalysis, 92:4, 903-924, DOI: 10.1111/j.1745-8315.2011.00410.x&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fanon, F. (2020). Black Skin, White Masks. Penguin Classics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Univ. of Chicago Press. (1994). The shell and the kernel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ghosh, Elisa. LACAN: THE UNCONSCIOUS IS STRUCTURED LIKE A LANGUAGE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;George, S., &amp;amp; Hook, D. (2022). Lacan and Race: Racism, identity, and psychoanalytic theory. Routledge, Taylor et Francis Group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Copjec, J. (2005). The horror reader. Routledge.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Review of Jantzen&#39;s &#39;William James and the Varieties of Postmodern Religious Experience&#39;</title>
      <link>/posts/william_james/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2023 20:39:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/william_james/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In “William James and the varieties of postmodern religious experience”, Grace M. Jantzen problematizes an interpretation of James’ scholarly work—specifically as it relates to mystical experience, the reliability of such accounts, as well as the role that religion has in a (post)modern society— that is popular amongst analytic philosophers of religion. This interpretation stresses the importance of an objective stand-point through which reports of mystical experience can be evaluated. It would seem at first that this is the only way to move beyond the impasse James’ creates in his discussion of mysticism: if  moments of ecstasy, or mystical episodes that cannot be explained through recourse to phenomenal reality “have the right” to be binding on those individuals who experience them, but not on others, how can this tell us anything about the evidential value of these experiences? James’ use of the word “right” suggests that he is posing a question quid juris—  how is the person who has this experience entitled to it? If the mystic is entitled to it by virtue of experiencing it and the one who has not experienced it is entitled to reject it, then it would seem that (in the absence of an “objective” arbiter) it is entirely appropriate to consign mystical experience to a “private, subjective” sphere “without political consequence”— which is precisely what analytic philosophers of religion have done (Jantzen). Janzten does concede that James “leaves himself wide open to such interpretations”(Jantzen). However, thinkers can be read against themselves and this is what Jantzen sets out to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kantian stricture that analytic philosophers of religion apply to mystical experience in their reception of James work— by relegating mystical experience to the realm of noumena— can only be accomplished, argues Jantzen, if a third conclusion that James’ reaches concerning the authority of mystical states is ignored. In this conclusion, James mentions the possibility of “other orders of truth”, suggesting an ontological pluralism that would thoroughly disrupt the clean Kantian divide between phenomena and noumena (Jantzen). Indeed, Jantzen interprets this third conclusion as an example of James attempting to “escape the Kantian strictures on knowledge of the noumenal” (Jantzen).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another consequence of this privileging of the purely “objective”, disinterested stand-point when investigating mystical or religious phenomena is that not enough attention is paid to said experiences&amp;rsquo; historical determinants, nor their political implications. These considerations are  absolutely indispensable for an analysis of the varieties of religion in post-modernity, according to Jantzen. Granted, James is not a historian of religion nor a political scientist— his focus,  quite clearly expressed at the beginning of the Gifford lectures, is psychology. Jantzen recognizes this fact, and argues that acknowledging these factors does not detract from James’ goals in the least. She notes that his analysis of religious doctrine is inextricably linked to his “philosophy of pragmatism” that emphasizes the “organic connection” between theory and practice, or “thought and conduct”(Jantzen).  James’ view is that the truth-value of a proposition is not only determined by its fidelity to the “facts” but also by its practicability. This attentiveness to “conduct” is sorely missing from the analysis of analytic philosophers of religion. The practitioners of rarefied forms of theology are passionately denounced by James— their God is a “metaphysical monster” and their theological system does not even approach the status of truth (Jantzen).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analytic philosophers of religion have been able to maintain their position by disavowing James’ Hegelianism. Hegel’s  theory of critical sociality precludes any privileging of a “stand-pointless” judgment; one cannot simply appeal to the imperative of observing things as they actually exist because Hegel’s project calls into question the “putative objectivity” of immediate sense experience (Jantzen). This crude empiricism fails because it does not have a concept, or theory of the whole. One cannot arrive at a conclusion about the value of something by dint of accumulating “facts”. The space of reason “arises within a shared linguistic and cultural system”(Jantzen).  As such, Jantzen argues that a study of mystical experience must take into account the socio-political landscape which is constitutive of them (Hindus have visions of Shiva, Chrisitans of Jesus, Muslims of Mohammad), and more broadly, the social construction of religion itself. Jantzen realizes that this is not a view that she can directly attribute to James himself, but nonetheless she argues it must lie at the core of any ethical pragmatism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to now evaluate Jantzen’s argument; strengths and certain weaknesses that I identified in the text. I think that Jantzen’s repudiation of the analytic position was well-argued, even though this meant, as mentioned earlier in the essay, reading James against himself. I think this is a good strategy because it brings to our attention what may have been dismissed as trivial in earlier readings of James’ work— the opposition between what is “essential” or “inessential” in the text is unsettled and called into question. Jantzen’s historicist approach also struck me as (although this can be attributed to the prejudices that I brought to my reading of the essay) altogether more convincing than the claim that there exists a position of pure objectivity from which one can dismiss personal experiences. However, that we are all informed by social and cultural biases, is a statement that I think hardly anybody would deny— and so I was left wondering if the arguments made by the analytic philosophers of religion moved beyond a Kantian denunciation of mystical experience. Indeed, throughout the essay, Jantzen refers to this group without ever mentioning its members or their specific arguments, and so I thought her argument operated at a somewhat general register. On the issue of generality or abstraction, I also think that Jantzen’s article would have benefited from more clarity concerning the usage of the word “postmodern”. A working definition is not offered in the article, and this left me with many questions. Jantzen does not seem to conceive of post-modernism along the same lines as Lyotard or Jameson, instead,  I thought that the definition of postmodernity operative in the essay viewed it as something inaugurated by political and social tumult, or perhaps characterized by multiple, contradictory religious prejudices that merely conceal structures of power.  I also found myself wondering if Jantzen was linking postmodernism with the impulse to historicize and remain attentive to ideological motivations— if such a link can be made, then are we to think of Hegel, Gadamer, and James as theorists of the postmodern? Are the analytic philosophers of religion merely offering encomiums to their own ideological biases, with nothing more to say?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The relationship between secularism and progressivism is something that Jantz comments on in the final pages of the essay. She argues that those who claim that a progressive politics can only emerge in the absence of religion are categorically wrong. However, I think that Jantz’s position is actually quite similar to the one she argues against. She writes, “rejection of religious experience by critical and progressive thinkers would simply abandon the field to those who conscript religious experience to devastating and reactionary ends” (Jantzen). Her statement categorizes those who have faith into two categories: the senseless reactionary and the “critical and progressive thinker”. Is this entirely different from the categorization that the secular progressive makes between the enlightened agnostic and the savage believer? Is this categorization also not an act of ideological mystification— completely ignoring the political determinants of radicalism? Jantzen has, throughout the essay, reminded us of the necessity to contextualize matters concerning religious experience, and even asks the Foucaldian question: “What political and cultural  technologies of power remain unchallenged if religious experience is construed as private unsituated intensity?” (Jantzen). If religious experience has socio-political determinants then surely the same thing can be said of religious extremism or fanaticism. Insofar as the spectral figure of the extremist is the Other of a secular, civilized society, then its role in producing this Other must also be investigated. I will end with a quote from a recent book that I read criticizing precisely this attitude, that is, pragmatist or Habermasian approaches to sociality, which I find  pertinent to my analysis: “Unthinkable within such a framework is that some might be excluded from or choose to opt out of the space of reasons: the space is bounded with all exits and entrances sealed. This precludes the possibility of radical dissensus and therefore of drastic change: the terms of rational agency are already determined such that alternative forms of practical rationality are ruled out from the outset as infeasible, ridiculous, violent, dangerous, undemocratic… or nonhuman” (Comay).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;works-cited&#34;&gt;Works Cited&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jantzen, Grace M. “William James and the Varieties of Religious Experience.” 2004, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.4324/9780203413135&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.4324/9780203413135&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comay, Rebecca. The Dash&amp;ndash;the Other Side of Absolute Knowing. MIT Press, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Wordsworth and Clare</title>
      <link>/posts/wordsworth/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 21:45:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/wordsworth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The poet&amp;rsquo;s relation to nature (pace those who view poetic creation as inspiration that comes from without) is informed, if not overdetermined by historical, social, and cultural contingencies. Both Woodsworth’s and Clare’s poems are marked by an intimacy that can only arise out of a partial identification with the environment they represent. Both poems also evoke feelings of nostalgia and portray the poet as an isolated individual. However, in “I wandered lonely as a cloud”, the poet’s isolation is not to be understood negatively, but is rather the precondition of his union with nature and communal gamboling; his nostalgia is the yearning for an immediate, unmediated experience of nature. The poet’s isolation in “Helpstone” is a form of alienation precipitated by “Accursed wealth” and relations of exploitation — the loss of a once sublime natural landscape is mourned (“Helpstone”, 127).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While both “I wandered lonely as a cloud” and “Helpstone” express the interdependence of the constitutive elements of nature, this awareness has a thorough-going political dimension in Clare’s poem, (betraying the poet’s working-class origins) whereas in Woodsworth it retracts into bourgeois idealism. Clare’s “Genius” is encumbered by an economic imperative — “Where bustling Labour drives the hours long” — and one even gets the sense that Clare is referring to himself when he speaks of the “low” Genius’ inability to transcend or “rise” above his “vulgar” material conditions (“Helpstone”, 6). We can contrast this with Woodsworth’s Poet, who, removed from the constraints of labour, “floats on high o’er vales and hills” (“I wandered lonely as a cloud”, 2).There are no moments of ecstasy in Clare’s poem, where one only encounters nature negatively— the village is “Unknown to grandeur” and the Genius is “Unknown nor heeded” (“Helpstone”, 3, 9). Since Labour violently dispossesses and subjugates the Genius, he is barred from any sort of literary recognition— “No minstrel boasting to advance thy name” (“Helpstone”, 4).  Unlike Woodsworth’s Poet, Clare’s identification with the environment does not result in “pleasure” and “glee” (“I wandered lonely as a cloud, 14, 23). Rather, it debases him since the domination of nature cannot be separated from the domination of man, as is evident from Clare’s personifying his village“—And thy mean village lifts its lowly head” (“Helpstone”, 2). The personification of the daffodils in Woodsworth’s poem, on the other hand— “Tossing their heads in a sprightly dance”—  elevates the Poet to a state where he “could not but be gay”(“I wandered lonely as a cloud”, 12, 15).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The enclosure of land also results in a bifurcation— Clare can no longer straightforwardly identify with nature because it has been disfigured by “Accursed wealth” (“Helpstone”, 127). Even if such an identification were possible, it would not result in the blissful harmony experienced by Woodsworth’s Poet but rather a “useless Ignorance” that “slumbers life away”(“Helpstone”, 8. This bifurcation does not exist in “I wandered lonely as a cloud”, since the Poet’s identification with nature is not prohibited by a calamitous event such as the enclosure of the commons. While the failure of identification in Helpstone clearly demonstrates Clare’s disapprobation of the effects of a then-nascent capitalism, as well as his ecological consciousness, the Poet’s identification with nature in “I wandered lonely as a cloud” does not have these political overtones. Rather, it serves to fill his heart with pleasure upon experiencing union with nature— he has the privilege of experiencing solitude as “bliss” (“I wandered lonely as a cloud”, 22). Reading Clare’s poem one can only imagine a monochromatic, barren landscape while Woodsworth’s Poet encounters “golden daffodils” and lively trees that are “Fluttering and dancing in the breeze” (“I wandered lonely as a cloud”, 4, 6). There is thus an incredibly pronounced incongruity between a landscape that is teeming with life and one that is corpse-like, hostile to all life-forms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reader encounters in Clare’s poem a brief description of  “humble Helpstone” prior to this destruction, one which “fond memory clings” to (“Helpstone”, 1, 117).  It is clear that Clare’s memory of this veritable garden of Eden is a part of his identity, such that the physical enclosure of Helpstone is equally an enclosure of his soul. Consequently, this enclosure, that which alienates the labourer resulting in the irretrievable loss of “our labour and bread” (notice how, when referring to the destructive force that dispossesses the labourer Clare uses “thou”and “thine”, using “our” to emphasize the loss, not only of a physical environment, but an entire community) , produces another bifurcation, this time between past and present (“Helpstone”, 132). This discontinuity is so pronounced that there appears to be no possible way to contain the destructive force, or undo its effects by  returning to an idyllic past. It seems that the only thing to do is “bow down” and “clear a way” for the impersonal force ravaging the land (“Helpstone”, 134). Once again, this bifurcation does not exist in “I wandered lonely as a cloud”, where, in complete contrast to “Helpstone”, the joy of the Poet emerges precisely out of the continuity between past and present, as is evidenced by the Poet’s recollection, “ In vacant or in pensive mood/They flash upon that inward eye” (“I wandered lonely as a cloud”, 21-22).  This continuity also allows for the possibility of narrative progress— the Poet is at first “lonely as a cloud”, but is then embraced by “jocund company” (“I wandered lonely as a cloud”, 1, 16). Conversely, in “Helpstone”, the physical enclosure of land terminates historical possibility and consigns the community to oblivion, to a “dark corner of obscurity”; there is no possibility of escape (“Helpstone”, 120).
While Clare confronts the impermanence of an environment untouched by economic forces, forced to reckon with his loneliness, Woodsworth revels in the infinitude of his cosmic vision of “stars that shine” in a “never-ending line” and is able to overcome his loneliness through union with nature (“I wandered lonely as a cloud”, 7,8).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
