<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Omar&#39;s blog</title>
    <link>/posts/</link>
    <description>Omar&#39;s blog (Posts)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 May 2022 22:05:02 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Is the Yeshiva obsolete?</title>
      <link>/posts/grade/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2022 22:05:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/grade/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It appears at times that what is meant by modernism— a vague, almost vacuous term if not contextualized properly— is that period in human history characterized by the alienation of Man. Rapid industrial development and various technological innovations have provided society with those tools that are necessary for it to take seriously the Kantian exhortation that we ought to emerge from our state of self-incurred immaturity. Yet these modern developments are simultaneously instruments of destruction, subjugation, and indeed, alienation. I am not concerned, in this essay, with the Marxian concept of alienation as the estrangement of the laborer from the fruits of his labor, but rather, alienation understood in a more existential sense; as displacement, spiritual impoverishment, and cultural and religious fragmentation. What, then, should we make of this sense of loss? Is our only hope to return assiduously to religious systems of meaning, refusing the cynical realism of modernity? Or do the world-historical catastrophes set in motion by modernity— the Shoah, in particular— allow us to rethink such concepts as God, history, and man? More concretely, what is the role of religious institutions, such as the Yeshiva, in the modern world? Are they merely the vestiges of premodernity, attempting to resuscitate a religious world-view experiencing its death throes, or can they help us navigate the modern world? My Quarrel with Hersh Rayner is concerned with precisely this tension. The complexity of this tension or antagonism defies a simple resolution and it is for this reason that I will argue that the representation of the Yeshiva in My Quarrel is marked by a certain ambivalence; it does not straightforwardly identify the Yeshiva with ideal piety, nor is it a paean dedicated to the glorification of the supposedly redemptive qualities of modernity. I will argue that while there exists a fundamental incongruence between Chaim and Hersh’s positions, it is this incongruence, this antagonism, that is the very condition of possibility for their debate to unfold. If we understand Chaim’s position not as a rejection of Jewish theology, but rather one that has immense religious significance, it can be argued that both characters are, in the final analysis, grappling with the same problems and questions, despite offering different solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an urgent, perhaps even dangerous, question that can be posed upon finishing My Quarrel: is it possible to take seriously the antagonism that is constitutive of Jewish study and identity if this antagonism calls into question the study of Torah, or some other fundamental tenet of Jewish theology itself? Even in the fiercest of disagreements what is always presupposed is that one begins from the Torah. It is from this starting point that interpretive differences may abound. What is to be done when this ground is demolished? Given the radicality of this proposition, one may, like Hersh, reject it a priori. However, this rejection would imply that Chaim’s position— his concerns and questions— have a purely secular import and are unintelligible when applied to religious discourse. This is far from the case. If Chaim retorts that the first question Hersh addresses to him is unintelligible— “Your question, Hersh Rasseyner, is no question at all. I do what I have to do”— it is not because he rejects Jewish spirituality in toto but recognizes that spirituality, in a modern context, must be re-imagined ( not re-jected) (Grade 24). Indeed, Chaim is entirely critical of the developments of modernity which he sees as initiating a crisis within Judaism. Addressing Hersh’s accusations, he solemnly proclaims that “You don’t understand that I myself say ‘No’ to the world as it is. And yet I force myself to say ‘Yes’ because I believe in my street” (Grade 25). The “as it is” is of crucial importance and is indicative of Chaim’s firm belief that a world-view that espouses a sort of radical asceticism is seldom helpful in navigating the treacherous terrain of modernity. If the alienation of the subject is constitutive of modernity, then what good can possibly come from a withdrawal from the world? Should not the duty of the Rebbe be to foster meaningful relationships with the “the porters with their backs broken from carrying their loads; the artisans sweating at their workbenches” (Grade 25)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is thus a dialectical tension between Chaim’s ‘Yes’ and ‘No’ — declarations both of affirmation and negation— that allow him to navigate not only the modern world, but Jewishness itself. Notice how Hersh refuses even the possibility of affirmation, collapsing this dialectic— in a manner befitting his misanthropic disposition, he defines Jewishness negatively, “I have heard that your pamphlet, your excuse for a book, is called Yes. But I tell you, ‘No!’” (Grade 24). In a sense, then, Chaim is even more of a “traditional” Jew than Hersh because he does not disavow this contradiction! Although Hersh believes that Chaim has a phantasmic conception of Judaism, one must take seriously Chaim’s  rejoinder that it is Hersh who has “dreamed up a world and then renounced it” (Grade 31).  I would go even further than Chaim—Hersh has dreamed up an insular conception of Judaism itself. Traditionalism, as is argued by Joseph Katz, can be understood as a modern phenomenon. By expressing a desire to return to an idyllic, supposedly authentic past, those who espouse the most stringent forms of orthodoxy, paradoxically, introduce new content into religious tradition. Indeed, calling upon God to justify His ways, far from being blasphemous, is well-documented in Jewish history. Was it not Job who challenged his Lord by crying out in agony, “If only I knew how to find God, how to enter his court, I would state my case before Him and set out my arguments in full; then I should learn what answer he would give and find out what he had to say” (Job 23:3-5)? Did not Judaism begin with an agreement, a contract between Man and God? There were different methods of teaching even in rabbinic Judaism. Did not Hillel respond to the gentile with a gentle playfulness when he had been rebuked harshly by Shammai beforehand?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As such, this tension persists between their positions, even though Hersh is unable to, or unwilling to acknowledge it. While refusing to acknowledge the religious significance of Chaim’s position, Hersh does not reject the importance of disputations in the history of Judaism— “For you, who are on the outside, Hasidism and Musar are just two opposing points of view… But actually, they both strengthened Judaism and their dispute is long forgotten” (Grade 29). The irony here is, of course, palpable. Hersh’s denigration of Chaim’s position is aimed precisely at the idea that Chaim trivializes Judaism. Concerning the dispute between Hasidism and Musar he says, “If the rabbis once fought over  Hasidism and Musar it was because they were afraid the new path would draw Jews away from strict observance” (Grade 29). But is Chaim not proposing precisely a “new path”?  It is only by preemptively designating Chaim an “outsider” that Hersh is able to evade his well-founded and provocative questions. He considers him to be an individual who “ran away from being Jewish” disguising his “flight with high-sounding phrases” (Grade 43).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chaim, cognizant of the antagonism that has allowed for the development of his own spirituality, is conciliatory rather than dismissive: “As I sat here listening to you, I sometimes thought I was listening to myself” (Grade 47).
Hersh, unbeknownst to himself, reveals that, conceptually, his  “Jewish history” depends on a form of retroactive causation; he canonizes certain disputes in the history of Judaism while refusing to acknowledge the religious significance of his disagreement with Chaim. For Hersh, these were necessary disputes, while Chaim’s grievances are merely contingent.  He can only come to this conclusion retroactively— he does not realize that this “return to the past” is itself an act of interpretation and reordering, and it is only through this temporal reconstruction that he is able to legitimize his own conception of Judaism. It would be unfair, then, to say that Chaim is the sole character in this story concerned with reimagining Judaism. His reimagining disrupts this linear temporality and embraces fully the uncertain and speculative. One can imagine that if Hersh were miraculously transported to a future where Chaim’s position was taken more seriously by Jewish intelligentsia,  he would say of their disagreement the very same thing he now says of the dispute between Musar and Hasidism: “for those who observe and practice Jewishness they are one and the same” (Grade 29).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An investigation into the category of Jewishness must necessarily examine the role of study in producing subjects. Study should not be understood— and this is particularly true of religious study— as the acquisition of information but rather as a process of subjectivation. But the subject is always haunted by the possibility of its demolition or disappearance. This forces those tasked with teaching to confront an unsettling question: what is to be done when this process is disrupted by a historical trauma? If the destruction of the Temple rendered obsolete certain forms of worship, but not Judaism as a whole, then must we take seriously the argument that the Shoah also calls for a &amp;ldquo;re-imagining&amp;rdquo; of Judaism and the Yeshiva? We must keep in mind that this re-imagination is not a wholesale negation of the past, nor is it a simple acquiescence to modernity.  These are questions that are equally difficult both for the traditionalist and the secularist. Even the steadfast Hersh appears to falter when faced with them, bypassing the issue by a perfunctory maneuver: “The almighty helps. What difference does it make how you speak? The main thing is what you speak” (Grade 28). Having first flattened the dialectical relationship between the ‘Yes’ and the ‘No’, Hersh now privileges content over form. But his dismissal of the form of education as that which is merely tangential to the process of subjectivation also reveals the incertitude that plagues him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although  Hersh appears to have ready-made answers to all of Chaim’s queries, a certain anxiety belies his fiery passion. He yearns for the security and sense of wholeness that was once offered by the Yeshiva— “Each of us filed and polished his own soul… Then came the Germans” (Grade 36). Evidently, even Hersh acknowledges that a shift— what Levinas calls a “ruin of representation” — cosmic in its scope, has befallen Judaism and Jewish study. Herein lies the essence of trauma— the subject is forced to reckon with something that is utterly unfamiliar to it but is nonetheless transfixed by it and thus irreversibly changed. Hersh, in the face of the suspension of the symbolic order can only cry out “we want a more onerous code, more commandments, more laws, more prohibitions” — the only way to overcome the threat of the suspension is precisely through this excess.  (Grade 44).  Any change to the structure of the Yeshiva would be seen as a compromise bordering on heresy. Hersh fears that this change would result in a form of study in which “anything goes”, thereby undermining the rigor that is supposed to be constitutive of study. Chaim, however, does not want to trivialize study, nor does he conceive of Jewishness as a superfluous category after the trauma of the Shoah. He tells Hersh that “we, too, are after wholeness, not  a middle-of-the-road compromise” (Grade 48).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this “wholeness” is divided into two disparate parts: “Jewish tradition and secular culture” (Grade 48). It is only by embracing this schism, by “taking on a double responsibility” that a concrete solution might be arrived at. Moreover, Chaim argues that there are structural changes within the Jewish world itself that necessitate a rethinking of study. The fantasy of a self-sufficient Yeshiva no longer exists as the secular encroaches on the religious and every aspect of life is subject to the logic of capital— “So I won’t waste time telling you about the powerful and wealthy Jewish leaders who made the community of Israel into their footstool” (Grade 48). Chaim tells Hersh, “Reb Hesh, let us embrace—” (Grade 53). The dash at the end of the sentence, far from being an editorial mistake or authorial idiosyncrasy , signifies a certain incompleteness, gestures at a new beginning, and is inherently interruptive. It concretizes the speculative import of Chaim’s arguments. This ending is not cathartic, the reader does not witness the interlocutors put aside their differences in order to affirm some Absolute Truth. And yet, the possibility of reconciliation remains amidst the strife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;works-cited&#34; &gt;Works Cited
&lt;span&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#works-cited&#34;&gt;
        &lt;svg viewBox=&#34;0 0 28 23&#34; height=&#34;100%&#34; width=&#34;19&#34; xmlns=&#34;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71&#34; fill=&#34;none&#34; stroke-linecap=&#34;round&#34; stroke-miterlimit=&#34;10&#34; stroke-width=&#34;2&#34;/&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71&#34; fill=&#34;none&#34; stroke-linecap=&#34;round&#34; stroke-miterlimit=&#34;10&#34; stroke-width=&#34;2&#34;/&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Grade, Chaim, and Herbert H. Paper. &amp;ldquo;My Quarrel with Hersh Rasseyner&amp;rdquo;. 1982.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Wordsworth and Clare</title>
      <link>/posts/wordsworth/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2022 21:45:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/wordsworth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The poet&amp;rsquo;s relation to nature (pace those who view poetic creation as inspiration that comes from without) is informed, if not overdetermined by historical, social, and cultural contingencies. Both Woodsworth’s and Clare’s poems are marked by an intimacy that can only arise out of a partial identification with the environment they represent. Both poems also evoke feelings of nostalgia and portray the poet as an isolated individual. However, in “I wandered lonely as a cloud”, the poet’s isolation is not to be understood negatively, but is rather the precondition of his union with nature and communal gamboling; his nostalgia is the yearning for an immediate, unmediated experience of nature. The poet’s isolation in “Helpstone” is a form of alienation precipitated by “Accursed wealth” and relations of exploitation — the loss of a once sublime natural landscape is mourned (“Helpstone”, 127).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While both “I wandered lonely as a cloud” and “Helpstone” express the interdependence of the constitutive elements of nature, this awareness has a thorough-going political dimension in Clare’s poem, (betraying the poet’s working-class origins) whereas in Woodsworth it retracts into bourgeois idealism. Clare’s “Genius” is encumbered by an economic imperative — “Where bustling Labour drives the hours long” — and one even gets the sense that Clare is referring to himself when he speaks of the “low” Genius’ inability to transcend or “rise” above his “vulgar” material conditions (“Helpstone”, 6). We can contrast this with Woodsworth’s Poet, who, removed from the constraints of labour, “floats on high o’er vales and hills” (“I wandered lonely as a cloud”, 2).There are no moments of ecstasy in Clare’s poem, where one only encounters nature negatively— the village is “Unknown to grandeur” and the Genius is “Unknown nor heeded” (“Helpstone”, 3, 9). Since Labour violently dispossesses and subjugates the Genius, he is barred from any sort of literary recognition— “No minstrel boasting to advance thy name” (“Helpstone”, 4).  Unlike Woodsworth’s Poet, Clare’s identification with the environment does not result in “pleasure” and “glee” (“I wandered lonely as a cloud, 14, 23). Rather, it debases him since the domination of nature cannot be separated from the domination of man, as is evident from Clare’s personifying his village“—And thy mean village lifts its lowly head” (“Helpstone”, 2). The personification of the daffodils in Woodsworth’s poem, on the other hand— “Tossing their heads in a sprightly dance”—  elevates the Poet to a state where he “could not but be gay”(“I wandered lonely as a cloud”, 12, 15).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The enclosure of land also results in a bifurcation— Clare can no longer straightforwardly identify with nature because it has been disfigured by “Accursed wealth” (“Helpstone”, 127). Even if such an identification were possible, it would not result in the blissful harmony experienced by Woodsworth’s Poet but rather a “useless Ignorance” that “slumbers life away”(“Helpstone”, 8. This bifurcation does not exist in “I wandered lonely as a cloud”, since the Poet’s identification with nature is not prohibited by a calamitous event such as the enclosure of the commons. While the failure of identification in Helpstone clearly demonstrates Clare’s disapprobation of the effects of a then-nascent capitalism, as well as his ecological consciousness, the Poet’s identification with nature in “I wandered lonely as a cloud” does not have these political overtones. Rather, it serves to fill his heart with pleasure upon experiencing union with nature— he has the privilege of experiencing solitude as “bliss” (“I wandered lonely as a cloud”, 22). Reading Clare’s poem one can only imagine a monochromatic, barren landscape while Woodsworth’s Poet encounters “golden daffodils” and lively trees that are “Fluttering and dancing in the breeze” (“I wandered lonely as a cloud”, 4, 6). There is thus an incredibly pronounced incongruity between a landscape that is teeming with life and one that is corpse-like, hostile to all life-forms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reader encounters in Clare’s poem a brief description of  “humble Helpstone” prior to this destruction, one which “fond memory clings” to (“Helpstone”, 1, 117).  It is clear that Clare’s memory of this veritable garden of Eden is a part of his identity, such that the physical enclosure of Helpstone is equally an enclosure of his soul. Consequently, this enclosure, that which alienates the labourer resulting in the irretrievable loss of “our labour and bread” (notice how, when referring to the destructive force that dispossesses the labourer Clare uses “thou”and “thine”, using “our” to emphasize the loss, not only of a physical environment, but an entire community) , produces another bifurcation, this time between past and present (“Helpstone”, 132). This discontinuity is so pronounced that there appears to be no possible way to contain the destructive force, or undo its effects by  returning to an idyllic past. It seems that the only thing to do is “bow down” and “clear a way” for the impersonal force ravaging the land (“Helpstone”, 134). Once again, this bifurcation does not exist in “I wandered lonely as a cloud”, where, in complete contrast to “Helpstone”, the joy of the Poet emerges precisely out of the continuity between past and present, as is evidenced by the Poet’s recollection, “ In vacant or in pensive mood/They flash upon that inward eye” (“I wandered lonely as a cloud”, 21-22).  This continuity also allows for the possibility of narrative progress— the Poet is at first “lonely as a cloud”, but is then embraced by “jocund company” (“I wandered lonely as a cloud”, 1, 16). Conversely, in “Helpstone”, the physical enclosure of land terminates historical possibility and consigns the community to oblivion, to a “dark corner of obscurity”; there is no possibility of escape (“Helpstone”, 120).
While Clare confronts the impermanence of an environment untouched by economic forces, forced to reckon with his loneliness, Woodsworth revels in the infinitude of his cosmic vision of “stars that shine” in a “never-ending line” and is able to overcome his loneliness through union with nature (“I wandered lonely as a cloud”, 7,8).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Review of Jantzen&#39;s &#39;William James and the varieties of postmodern religious experience&#39;</title>
      <link>/posts/william_james/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2022 20:39:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/william_james/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In “William James and the varieties of postmodern religious experience”, Grace M. Jantzen problematizes an interpretation of James’ scholarly work—specifically as it relates to mystical experience, the reliability of such accounts, as well as the role that religion has in a (post)modern society— that is popular amongst analytic philosophers of religion. This interpretation stresses the importance of an objective stand-point through which reports of mystical experience can be evaluated. It would seem at first that this is the only way to move beyond the impasse James’ creates in his discussion of mysticism: if  moments of ecstasy, or mystical episodes that cannot be explained through recourse to phenomenal reality “have the right” to be binding on those individuals who experience them, but not on others, how can this tell us anything about the evidential value of these experiences? James’ use of the word “right” suggests that he is posing a question quid juris—  how is the person who has this experience entitled to it? If the mystic is entitled to it by virtue of experiencing it and the one who has not experienced it is entitled to reject it, then it would seem that (in the absence of an “objective” arbiter) it is entirely appropriate to consign mystical experience to a “private, subjective” sphere “without political consequence”— which is precisely what analytic philosophers of religion have done (Jantzen). Janzten does concede that James “leaves himself wide open to such interpretations”(Jantzen). However, thinkers can be read against themselves and this is what Jantzen sets out to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kantian stricture that analytic philosophers of religion apply to mystical experience in their reception of James work— by relegating mystical experience to the realm of noumena— can only be accomplished, argues Jantzen, if a third conclusion that James’ reaches concerning the authority of mystical states is ignored. In this conclusion, James mentions the possibility of “other orders of truth”, suggesting an ontological pluralism that would thoroughly disrupt the clean Kantian divide between phenomena and noumena (Jantzen). Indeed, Jantzen interprets this third conclusion as an example of James attempting to “escape the Kantian strictures on knowledge of the noumenal” (Jantzen).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another consequence of this privileging of the purely “objective”, disinterested stand-point when investigating mystical or religious phenomena is that not enough attention is paid to said experiences&amp;rsquo; historical determinants, nor their political implications. These considerations are  absolutely indispensable for an analysis of the varieties of religion in post-modernity, according to Jantzen. Granted, James is not a historian of religion nor a political scientist— his focus,  quite clearly expressed at the beginning of the Gifford lectures, is psychology. Jantzen recognizes this fact, and argues that acknowledging these factors does not detract from James’ goals in the least. She notes that his analysis of religious doctrine is inextricably linked to his “philosophy of pragmatism” that emphasizes the “organic connection” between theory and practice, or “thought and conduct”(Jantzen).  James’ view is that the truth-value of a proposition is not only determined by its fidelity to the “facts” but also by its practicability. This attentiveness to “conduct” is sorely missing from the analysis of analytic philosophers of religion. The practitioners of rarefied forms of theology are passionately denounced by James— their God is a “metaphysical monster” and their theological system does not even approach the status of truth (Jantzen).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analytic philosophers of religion have been able to maintain their position by disavowing James’ Hegelianism. Hegel’s  theory of critical sociality precludes any privileging of a “stand-pointless” judgment; one cannot simply appeal to the imperative of observing things as they actually exist because Hegel’s project calls into question the “putative objectivity” of immediate sense experience (Jantzen). This crude empiricism fails because it does not have a concept, or theory of the whole. One cannot arrive at a conclusion about the value of something by dint of accumulating “facts”. The space of reason “arises within a shared linguistic and cultural system”(Jantzen).  As such, Jantzen argues that a study of mystical experience must take into account the socio-political landscape which is constitutive of them (Hindus have visions of Shiva, Chrisitans of Jesus, Muslims of Mohammad), and more broadly, the social construction of religion itself. Jantzen realizes that this is not a view that she can directly attribute to James himself, but nonetheless she argues it must lie at the core of any ethical pragmatism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to now evaluate Jantzen’s argument; strengths and certain weaknesses that I identified in the text. I think that Jantzen’s repudiation of the analytic position was well-argued, even though this meant, as mentioned earlier in the essay, reading James against himself. I think this is a good strategy because it brings to our attention what may have been dismissed as trivial in earlier readings of James’ work— the opposition between what is “essential” or “inessential” in the text is unsettled and called into question. Jantzen’s historicist approach also struck me as (although this can be attributed to the prejudices that I brought to my reading of the essay) altogether more convincing than the claim that there exists a position of pure objectivity from which one can dismiss personal experiences. However, that we are all informed by social and cultural biases, is a statement that I think hardly anybody would deny— and so I was left wondering if the arguments made by the analytic philosophers of religion moved beyond a Kantian denunciation of mystical experience. Indeed, throughout the essay, Jantzen refers to this group without ever mentioning its members or their specific arguments, and so I thought her argument operated at a somewhat general register. On the issue of generality or abstraction, I also think that Jantzen’s article would have benefited from more clarity concerning the usage of the word “postmodern”. A working definition is not offered in the article, and this left me with many questions. Jantzen does not seem to conceive of post-modernism along the same lines as Lyotard or Jameson, instead,  I thought that the definition of postmodernity operative in the essay viewed it as something inaugurated by political and social tumult, or perhaps characterized by multiple, contradictory religious prejudices that merely conceal structures of power.  I also found myself wondering if Jantzen was linking postmodernism with the impulse to historicize and remain attentive to ideological motivations— if such a link can be made, then are we to think of Hegel, Gadamer, and James as theorists of the postmodern? Are the analytic philosophers of religion merely offering encomiums to their own ideological biases, with nothing more to say?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The relationship between secularism and progressivism is something that Jantz comments on in the final pages of the essay. She argues that those who claim that a progressive politics can only emerge in the absence of religion are categorically wrong. However, I think that Jantz’s position is actually quite similar to the one she argues against. She writes, “rejection of religious experience by critical and progressive thinkers would simply abandon the field to those who conscript religious experience to devastating and reactionary ends” (Jantzen). Her statement categorizes those who have faith into two categories: the senseless reactionary and the “critical and progressive thinker”. Is this entirely different from the categorization that the secular progressive makes between the enlightened agnostic and the savage believer? Is this categorization also not an act of ideological mystification— completely ignoring the political determinants of radicalism? Jantzen has, throughout the essay, reminded us of the necessity to contextualize matters concerning religious experience, and even asks the Foucaldian question: “What political and cultural  technologies of power remain unchallenged if religious experience is construed as private unsituated intensity?” (Jantzen). If religious experience has socio-political determinants then surely the same thing can be said of religious extremism or fanaticism. Insofar as the spectral figure of the extremist is the Other of a secular, civilized society, then its role in producing this Other must also be investigated. I will end with a quote from a recent book that I read criticizing precisely this attitude, that is, pragmatist or Habermasian approaches to sociality, which I find  pertinent to my analysis: “Unthinkable within such a framework is that some might be excluded from or choose to opt out of the space of reasons: the space is bounded with all exits and entrances sealed. This precludes the possibility of radical dissensus and therefore of drastic change: the terms of rational agency are already determined such that alternative forms of practical rationality are ruled out from the outset as infeasible, ridiculous, violent, dangerous, undemocratic… or nonhuman” (Comay).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;works-cited&#34; &gt;Works Cited
&lt;span&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#works-cited&#34;&gt;
        &lt;svg viewBox=&#34;0 0 28 23&#34; height=&#34;100%&#34; width=&#34;19&#34; xmlns=&#34;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;M10 13a5 5 0 0 0 7.54.54l3-3a5 5 0 0 0-7.07-7.07l-1.72 1.71&#34; fill=&#34;none&#34; stroke-linecap=&#34;round&#34; stroke-miterlimit=&#34;10&#34; stroke-width=&#34;2&#34;/&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;M14 11a5 5 0 0 0-7.54-.54l-3 3a5 5 0 0 0 7.07 7.07l1.71-1.71&#34; fill=&#34;none&#34; stroke-linecap=&#34;round&#34; stroke-miterlimit=&#34;10&#34; stroke-width=&#34;2&#34;/&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jantzen, Grace M. “William James and the Varieties of Religious Experience.” 2004, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.4324/9780203413135&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.4324/9780203413135&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comay, Rebecca. The Dash&amp;ndash;the Other Side of Absolute Knowing. MIT Press, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
